Introduction

However injurious wild animals may be to man, he should not forget that he himself is very often the cause of their undue destructiveness. When destroying his crops, they are only following the instincts with which they have been endowed by the Creator. Ruled by All-wise laws, every animal fills its appointed place exactly, existing not alone for itself but forming a necessary part of the vast system of Nature. One class of animals keep in check certain plants; others prevent the too great increase of these, while those having few enemies are not prolific. Man interferes unwisely, and the order is broken. It is true that, to some extent, an interference with the natural regulations of the animal creation is necessary to the progress of civilization. Man appropriates to himself the food of many animals, but as they continue to devour this wherever found, he must therefore sometimes destroy them or lose his property.

But, before waging war upon any animal, let us study its habits, and look well to the consequences which would follow its extermination. We must remember that it is an undeniable fact, that the dangerous increase of any species is due to the destruction of its natural enemies; and, indeed, would we stop the ravages of a vegetable-eating animal, the easiest and most certain way generally is to encourage the increase of these ememies.

But some men think animals unworthy of study, and do not know the injurious from the beneficial. A farmer’s poultry have been killed by some carnivorous mammals or birds, and he therefore destroys every one of these, large or small, indiscriminately, whether found about his farm-yard or out in the fields. Some birds injure his crops, and so every bird that ever ate a grain of corn is shot, while many, which are not known to do any harm, are killed lest they should; and his boys are hence encouraged to destroy blackbird’s nests, and they very naturally extend their destructiveness to every other bird’s nest they can find. The meadow-mice are injurious, and he accordingly wages war upon the shrews and moles, which he confounds with the mice, or accuses of performing their work. He knows some snakes are venomous, and so pronounces all reptiles “deadly” and “horrible things,” to be dreaded and destroyed. His crops are affected by insects, and he eagerly kills the carnivorous species with the others. And then gnawing mammals kill his trees and destroy his crops, and the insects multiply alarmingly, and he wonders “why such worse than useless creatures were created!”

A more careful study of animals would surely benefit our farmers. I would earnestly commend the subject to their special consideration. If they say they cannot spare time to watch the habits of animals, then let them encourage their children to do so, not alone that they may endeavor to learn, for practical purposes, the injurious from the beneficial, but also because of the good influence produced on mind and morals by the study of Nature—a study which will become the source of much profit and pleasure, as soon as the observer once begins earnestly to investigate Nature’s truths; and the interest will increase in proportion to the knowledge gained. Every farmer’s son and daughter should be naturalists; they have the best of opportunities for it. A few minutes spent at the right time would often reveal to them facts which naturalists have labored days in vain to discover . Workmen in the field have frequently passing under their eyes things which the naturalist would travel miles to see; and they daily and hourly witness things it would profit them much to observe. A farmer eagerly kills a harmless snake, and thinks he has done well. But it is not so. Let him examine its mouth, and he will find no [sic] poison[1] fangs there; and if he opens its stomach, it will be found to contain only insects, or, perhaps, meadow-mice. It takes but a moment to observe these things, yet, if he uses well the knowledge gained in this moment, it may prove to him of great value.

Farmers must not suppose that, in order to study animals profitably, they are obliged first to read scientific books. These are of much importance, but not all that is to be observed. A knowledge of the scientific names of species is of great value, enabling any one to learn the habits of animals not well known from others, while the imperative necessity for a system of scientific names in any extended study of natural history is too apparent to need comment. Common names may be used locally in conversation, or written, for want of better; but numerous misapplications and errors are sure to result. Farmers may be—and, to their credit be it said, many are— well aquainted with the habits of the animals about them, even though they know nothing of scientific names. These, however, by careful observation, have learned to distinguish certainly and readily each animal, and are not likely to consider moles, shrews, and meadow-mice as one and the same.

Let any farmer spend a few leisure half hours in observing the habits of animals, and then ask himself if the time thus spent has been wasted. True, he may not always have been in any way pecuniarily benefitted; but many men now-a-days realize a desire for knowledge whether that knowledge brings direct pecuniary profit or not; and while years spent in studying the words of dead languages, the fine arts, and man’s various creations, are taught to be profitably used, might it not be well to devote a few hours to the study of God’s language and fine arts, that their beauties too may be appreciated and understood?

[1] The correct term here is actually venom, not poison.

Black-Squirrel

[Plate VI.b, Photo 5]

Sciurus niger [Linnæus, 1758]

Description.—This is a little larger than the migratory squirrel. It is all over jet-black, with the exception of a few whitish hairs on the under surface. The fur is very soft and glossy; the hairs on the back are not annulated, as in Sciurus migratorius. There are no varieties in color.

This species is considered by some naturalists to be a variety of the migratory squirrel; and it possibly may be so. It has not been seen to breed with this squirrel, however; and, if only a variety in color, it is a remarkably permanent one in a species so variable. Some of its habits seem to differ from those of the other, though they are mostly the same.

The black-squirrel has been observed through the Middle States, in Michigan and Wisconsin; and Audubon and Bachman speak of specimens received from Lake Superior. I have seen them from Indiana in the Chicago market, and have shot some in Northern Illinois. It appears to be nowhere a common species; and all hunters agree that it disappears before the migratory squirrel, which is said to drive it off.

In Northern Illinois, I have always observed this squirrel in swamps or low river “bottoms,” and never in the high prairie groves, where the migratory squirrel is sometimes abundant. It is worthy of remark that it sometimes appears to love the vicinity of rivers or ponds of water.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The squirrel the author is referencing is a melanistic morph of either the species described earlier as the Large-Tailed Fox-Squirrel (page 55b, now known as the Western Fox Squirrel) and/or the species described earlier as the Migratory Squirrel (page 62b, now known as the Eastern Gray Squirrel).

The mutated allele responsible for melanism in both species appears to have first evolved within the Fox Squirrel complex and was then introgressed into the Eastern Gray Squirrel complex through a hybrid event. See Smithsonian Magazine: Interspecies Breeding Is Responsible for Some Squirrels’ Black Coloring.

There are two things to note:

In his account of the Migratory Squirrel, the author does reference a black variety of that squirrel, and that both color forms can come from the same litter. That matches how a Simple Mendelian Inheritance (Internet Link) melanistic allele would work.
In this species account of the author’s Black Squirrel, the author mentions that they are larger than the Migratory Squirrel.

Both of those considerations lead me to believe that this species account probably references a melanistic form of the Western Fox Squirrel.

When you come across a melanistic squirrel, which species it belongs to can be very difficult to identify visually without catching the animal.

Look around to see if there are any non-melanistic squirrels in the area. If there are and they are all the same species, then the melanistic squirrel likely is that species as well. If both species are in the area, well, just enjoy what you saw without an exact identification.

Unfortunately both species have been introduced into locations where they are not originally from so the use of a range map can be very unreliable, identifying other non-melanistic squirrels in the population is your best bet.

Striped Ground Squirrel, or Chipmuck

[Plate VIII.a, Photo 9]

Tamias striatus [Linnæus, 1758]

Description.—Length of head and body of the adult male, in summer, 6⅝ inches; vertebræ of tail, 4⅞ inches; tail to tip of longest hair, 5⅝ inches; breadth of tail, hairs in natural position, ⅝ inch. Upper parts brownish-gray, yellowish on the sides; two light yellow and four black lines on the back; the rump bright brown; belly white; tail not bushy nor flat, as in the true squirrels.

This beautiful and familiar little animal, with several other species, compose the genus Tamias. Though closely related to the true squirrels, they differ in habits and organization from their larger kindred, to suit their life on the ground. All the ground squirrels are of small size, living in burrows in the earth, and not habitually climbing trees. Their form is adapted to running on the ground and burrowing. They have capacious cheek-pouches, in which they carry large quantities of food to store up for winter provisions.

The chipmuck exists throughout the Eastern, Middle, as well as in some of the Western States, and as far north as latitude fifty degrees in the British Possessions. It is found in Minnesota, Iowa, and rarely, in Northern Missouri. I did not observe this species in the heavily timbered districts of Southern Illinois, and Colonel Ashley, of Jonesborough, informs me, it is rare, if found at all, in the southern part of the State. Though abundant in the prairie regions of Illinois, this species never leaves the woods. It is well known to every farmer living within its habitat, under the name of “Striped Ground Squirrel,” “Chipping Squirrel,” or “Chipmuck.” Audubon and Bachman say it is called “Hackee” at the East; but I have never heard that name applied to it here.

Wherever it abounds, the chipmuck attracts attention by its beauty, industrious habits, and cheerful activity. Not being a tree climber—and, in fact, preferring somewhat open ground to deep woods—nor fearing the neighborhood of man, it is found most abundantly burrowing under stumps, logs, or fences about cultivated land, and seems rather to increase than diminish in numbers, as the forests it inhabits are cleared for cultivation.

In spring and summer, chipmucks make love, rear their young, chase each other over the stumps and logs, in play, and enjoy themselves in various other ways; and with autumn and its harvest-time comes their season of hard work. We are not to suppose, however, that this work is at all disagreeable to them, as man’s duties are to him, when he will not cheerfully obey the laws of creation. They may now be seen hastening to and from their holes, their cheek-pouches distended with nuts, acorns, and seeds, or with grain stolen from the neighboring fields. Thus they continue to collect food till cold weather has set in, when they retire to their burrows, where, with well filled larders, they pass the winter comfortably, regardless of the cold winds which rage above them. This species closes the entrance to its burrow late in autumn, and appears to pass the winter in a state of semi-hibernation; for, though taking nourishment, and not torpid, it never comes out, except very rarely in long-continued mild weather.

Like the true squirrels, the chipmucks are properly nut-eaters, though they feed rather more upon the seeds of small plants than their arboreal relatives; nor do they subsist upon the buds of trees. Dr. Hoy informs me that he once observed a number of chipmucks climbing the bushes of the prickly ash (Xanthoxylum americanum), to obtain the berries which they were carrying to their burrows in considerable quantities. At another time, he saw one repeatedly climb a hickory and cut off the unripe nuts, which were brought to the ground, and, while yet covered with the green pericarp, placed in a hole at the root of the tree, which, however, was not its burrow; and he was told that the same individual was noticed to carry away nuts in this manner for some days. Though this species does not generally climb trees, except when pursued, I am inclined to think it does so voluntarily more frequently than is supposed.

The quantity of nuts, acorns, and seeds sometimes collected by these industrious little fellows is astonishing. They are frequently stored temporarily under logs, and in shallow holes under roots of trees, and afterwards removed to the burrow, at a more leisure season. I have known lazy people to watch the chipmucks in nutting time, and finding where they carried their stores, dig them out, saying they could thus get nuts faster than by picking them up themselves. In a burrow dug open in November, I found over half a bushel of hickory-nuts and acorns. These were not all in one place, but in four or five enlarged chambers, in different parts of the burrow, which was complicated, and consisted of several winding and intersecting passages, situated not over a foot below the surface. The entrance to the burrow was under a log, and the passages extended several feet on every side. A large nest of leaves and grass was placed above the surface, under the rotten log. Only one of the inhabitants was found, but he was quite active.

This ground squirrel is sociable; and sometimes, though not always, several pairs occupy the same burrow in winter, the store of food being common property. These, like the true squirrels, stand erect on their hind-feet, when eating, using the fore-paws as hands. The power of their incisors is wonderful; they cut with apparent ease through the shells of the seeds of wild plums, which would resist the point of tempered steel.

At times, the note of the chipmuck is a short deep cluck, repeatedly pronounced, without variation; and on a sunny day, he will sometimes utter it for an hour at a time, being meanwhile perched upon a stump or log; but more frequently the note is a shriller chip-chip. When alarmed, he utters a low chatter.

The amount of grain stolen by chipmucks is seldom of much value; though, where they are so abundant as to attack a field by hundreds, the result of their depredations may become quite an item of loss. The most serious cause of complaint against them is, the injury done by digging up corn when first planted. They go along the rows like the black-birds or spermophiles, and, guided by the sprouting blades, dig out the grains, or even take them before they sprout, and in this way frequently cause considerable damage. Chipmucks, generally, however, cannot be considered as great enemies to the farmer. They are oftener destroyed by the rapacious birds and mammals than the true squirrels, though, being considered of no value as food, they are not so frequently killed by man. Our small weasels are known to kill many; the mink often makes a meal of them; and even the foxes and wild-cats do not disdain to devour every unlucky little individual they can catch, while many are eaten by birds of prey; so that it is no matter of surprise that they should increase in cultivated districts, where they are in a measure protected from their natural enemies. When they become so numerous and destructive as to render it necessary to kill them off, they may be easily shot, or caught in any kind of a trap, as they are not at all suspicious; and they could probably be poisoned with arsenic, mixed with meal, and placed near their burrows. Several ferrets and terrier dogs would quickly clear a farm of them.

Other ground squirrels, closely resembling this in appearance and habits, exist in the western parts of the Union. I learn from Dr. Hoy that the four-lined ground squirrel (Tamias quadrivittatus) [Say, 1823] is found in Northern Wisconsin. This species, as observed by him in the Lake Superior region, appeared to have habits similar to those of Tamias striatus, though its voice differs so much as to be readily distinguishable from that of the latter, the note being longer and on a higher key.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The binomial nomenclature Tamias striatus [Linnæus, 1758] used by the author is still valid.

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Eastern Chipmunk’.

For more information on the Eastern Chipmunk, see:

Mammalian Species № 168: DOI:10.2307/3503819
ITIS Report for TSN 180207

Common Flying Squirrel

[Plate VII.b]

Pteromys volucella [Gmelin]

Description.—Length of old male, in March, from nose to root of tail, 4½ inches; vertebrae of tail, 3 inches; tail to end of hair, 3⅞ inches; hind-foot, 1¼ inches; breadth of tail, hairs in natural position, 1½ inches; width across the back from side to side, including fur, with the flying membrane extended, 4 inches; length of supplemental bone supporting the flying membrane, ¾ inch. This is certainly the most beautiful of our rodents. In the specimen before me, the long exquisitely soft fur, is slate-colored, tipped with creamy-yellowish drab on the back, the top of the tail brownish-drab; on the under surface, milk-white, tipped with cream color at the outer edges of the flying membrane and toward the tail, the under surface of which is very light brownish-yellow, tinged with cream. The large prominent eyes are black and lustrous; the whiskers long, and the nearly-naked ears rather large. The tail is densely clothed with soft hairs, and smoothly flattened; the feet are slender with small arched nails. The skin on the side is extended outward, to form a membrane which is attached to the legs, and to a supplemental slender curved bone, articulating with the joint of the fore-foot. When this membrane is stretched, the animal is enabled to sail through the air to some distance, by the force gained in descending from any elevated position, being aided in this by the flattened tail, which also serves as a rudder. It is not to be supposed, however, that the flying squirrel can propel itself through the air, like a bird or bat. The tail and membranes only form a sort of parachute, to buoy it up while the force gained by the descent, and by the spring made, carry it forward. When it is about to alight, it sails upward, by using the tail and hinder parts as a rudder, the momentum acquired being sufficient to raise it for some height at a considerable curve.

This, and several other American flying squirrels, and more from the Old World, form an exceedingly interesting group in the family Sciuridae, from the other members of which they differ materially in some of their habits. It probably exists throughout the whole eastern part of the Union. Its habitat being strictly among the trees, it cannot of course abide on the prairies, nor is it found generally in our smaller prairie groves; though it is as abundant in the large woods of Northern Illinois as elsewhere.

The flying squirrel is as active as the true species, but, unlike the rest of the family, it is nocturnal, and does not move about by day, except at times in cloudy weather. It prefers the twilight or darkness, when it leaves its retreat for amusement or in search of food, seldom travelling on the ground, but sailing gracefully from tree to tree, running up toward the top of one, and alighting lower upon the trunk of another. It is gregarious, living in hollow trees in large companies. It usually prevails in greater numbers, wherever found at all, than is generally supposed. If, in passing through the woods, any one will strike the sides of old hollow trees, he will frequently see a number of these singular and beautiful little animals rush out of a hole, and sail off to the neighboring trees. It does not build nests of leaves among the branches, like the true squirrels. I am informed by Mr. Brendel, of Peoria, however, that a female was observed by him to bring forth in a deserted bird’s nest. From three to six young are produced at a birth. Its food appears to be similar to that of the true squirrels. It eats corn and other grain, though, as it does not willingly leave the trees, the amount is probably inconsiderable, compared with that taken by the true species.

Flying squirrels appear, sometimes at least, to lay up stores of food for winter, at which time, they are active. I am informed of a number of instances in which they have entered the garrets of cabins in the woods to feed upon the corn deposited there.

A specimen kept in a cage became quite tame in a few days. Unless disturbed, it remained quiet during the day, curled up in its nest, with the head drawn down to the abdomen, and the flat tail laid over its head and upon the back. It would take food offered it during the day, but the light seemed to be painful to its eyes. In the evening, it began to spring and climb about the cage, and was active all night. This species has frequently been known to take up its residence, voluntarily, in or about human dwellings. It is quite easily domesticated, and being gentle, and very beautiful, makes a pleasant and interesting pet[1].

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The binomial name Pteromys volucella [Gmelin] used by the author is not currently an accepted name.

The species the author is referencing is the species currently referred to as Glaucomys volans [Linnaeus, 1758].

Originally described by Linnaeus in 1758 as Mus volans, the genus Mus was used as a taxonomy dumping ground for rodents that did not yet have an identifiable genus described to place them in.

In 1778, Pallas moved the species into the squirrel genus Sciurus and renamed the specific name to volucella, resulting in the the binomial name Sciurus volucella.

In 1800, Cuvier assigned the genus name Pteromy to flying squirrels using a Eurasian flying squirrel as the type species.

Sometime in the 19th century, perhaps first by Harlan in Fauna Americana (1825), this flying squirrel was moved into the genus Pteromy giving it the binomial name Pteromys volucella used by the author. The author cites Gmelin as the authority but I do not believe he is referencing the move into Pteromy.

In 1908, Thomas saw that Eurasian and American flying squirrels were different enough to warrant distinct genera and assigned the genus name Glaucomys for American flying squirrels.

The original species name volans takes priority over volucella by the rules of taxonomy nomenclature, giving us the currently accepted binomial name of Glaucomys volans [Linnaeus, 1758].

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Southern Flying Squirrel’.

For more information on the Southern Flying Squirrel, see:

Mammalian Species № 78: DOI:10.2307/3504026
ITIS Report for TSN 180170

[1] Please note that the author mentions this species is both gregarious (communal) and nocturnal. Much like sugar gliders, attempting to keep flying squirrels as pets is likely to be psychologically harmful to the squirrel. Please refrain from attempting to do so.

Common White-Footed Wood-Mouse

[Plate X.b]

Mus leucopus [Rafinesque, 1818]

Description.—Animals of this species vary much in size, adult specimens being from 2½ to 3¾ inches in length. The length of the tail, as compared with that of the body, also varies, being usually, however, a little shorter. The colors of the upper parts also vary in different specimens and at different seasons. Length of a large female, in August, from nose to root of tail, 3¾ inches; tail, 2⅞ inches; hind-foot thirteen-sixteenths of an inch. The upper parts are light brownish-yellow, with a stripe darker along the back. The yellow color is clearest on the cheeks and along the sides. The feet and entire under surface of the body are pure white. Other summer specimens are bluish-gray on the back. Upper parts, of a young specimen, of a uniform blackish ash-color, without any yellow. Though this may rarely be mistaken for the common house-mouse, which it somewhat resembles in form, it is at once distinguishable by its pure white belly and feet.

The white-footed wood-mouse is known under the names of “Deer Mouse,” “Buck Mouse,” “White-footed Field Mouse,” and, in common with the “Wood Mouse” (Jaculus labradorius)[1] and “Jumping Mouse.” It appears to exist throughout the wooded portions of the United States generally from the Atlantic to the Pacific. In this vicinity, the Mus leucopus appears to inhabit the timber only. I never observed one on the prairie. It is found in wooded farms, where it is more or less injurious to the farmer, carrying off and devouring grain, destroying various young plants, and occasionally doing much mischief by gnawing the bark of fruit-trees. On the whole, however, it cannot be considered very injurious. Though it may inhabit grain-fields in harvest time, it is decidedly a timber lover, and never breeds nor takes up its residence permanently in large fields, clear of trees, stumps, and logs. Its home is usually in an old stump or fallen log, under the bark of decayed trees, and sometimes in hollow trees, at a considerable height above the ground. It sometimes takes possession of deserted birds’ nests, and occasionally builds in the branches of trees. Dr. Hoy informs me that he has seen several of its nests in Southern Wisconsin. They were usually placed among the thick branches of a thorn, at a height of 8 or 10 feet from the ground. The nests were composed of grass, and were of a globular form, the entrance being a small hole on one side. I have also found nests on the ground, under logs, and once in August, found a female, about to bring forth young, in a nest of grass under a small block of wood, on a low river-bottom. I have not observed this species burrowing in the ground, and it appears rarely, if ever, to do so in the woods.

This mouse is sometimes gregarious, as many as a dozen having been found together in winter. I am informed of numerous instances in which several have been observed inhabiting the same hole in a tree with a family of flying squirrels. Neither species being at all pugnacious, they doubtless live together in harmony.

The white-footed wood-mouse feeds chiefly upon the leaves and seeds of various grasses, and other herbaceous plants, with nuts, acorns, and the seeds of basswood, maple, and other trees; grain is also eaten greedily by it in the fields. It lays up considerable stores of food for winter. Mr. Joseph Kennicott informs me that, in Western New York, he found within a stump in a clover-field, several quarts of clean seed of red clover, collected by a family of these mice. In storing up buckwheat, beech-nuts, and some other nuts and seeds, they strip off the shell, or covering to the kernel, and frequently a quart or two of the cleaned kernels of beech-nuts or various seeds will be found in their holes. Why this is done is not apparent. The mice would scarcely take so much trouble merely to save room occupied by the shells, and these fleshy kernels cannot keep as well when thus deprived of their natural covering.

This species is active in winter, like the rest of the genus, moving about a good deal on top of the snow, as well as below it, and sometimes traveling a long distance at this season. Mr. Laurence Koebelin tells me that, in cold weather, in December, he found one which had collected grass and formed a large nest in a pile of wood within two days after it had been cut.

The female exhibits much affection for her young. These, when small, I have always found attached to her teats, in which way she would carry them off, moving, unless chased, with great caution, as though she feared to injure them. A neighbor relates that, in turning over a log in the woods, he exposed one of these mice, which, instead of jumping off rapidly, moved slowly away along a small log, and was observed to have several young attached to her teats. Her movements being watched with interest, one of the young was seen to be brushed off and fall among the grass, the mother passing on out of sight. The young mouse left was quite helpless, and, continued to utter a low squeak. After a while, the mother returned to it, and though her movements could no longer be observed, the voice of the young mouse ceased, and, upon examination of the spot, it was found to have disappeared with the mother. It is not to be supposed, however, that the young of this mouse are attached to the mammae of the parent like those of the opossum.

Caged specimens do not eat flesh, and are not at all pugnacious. One kept for some time was very timid, did not bite when taken in the hand, nor did it become irritated when teased; yet remained discontented with captivity, showing no inclination to burrow in the earth at the bottom of its cage. When liberated upon the floor, it moved by sudden springs, holding high its long tail.

This species is active on the ground, and climbs readily. It dreads the usual enemies of small, timber-loving quadrupeds, though being nocturnal, it probably escapes the attacks of hawks. It must be much preyed upon, however, by owls; and weasels are said to be among its worst enemies. I have in several instances found the milk-snake (Ophiobolus eximius)[2] under logs and in old stumps, in suspicious proximity to the nests of this mouse; and other snakes, inhabiting the woods, also probably devour it. That it has numerous enemies is shown by its not increasing more rapidly—since it is a prolific species. I have usually found from four to six young in a nest; and there are two to three litters a year.

This is a beautiful little animal, possessing a graceful form and delicate colors, and would make a very interesting cage pet.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

This species is now placed within the genus Peromyscus [Gloger, 1841] as Peromyscus leucopus [Rafinesque, 1818].

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘White-footed Mouse’.

For more information on the White-footed Mouse, see:

Mammalian Species № 247: DOI:10.2307/3503904
ITIS Report for TSN 180278

[1] Currently referred to by the binomial name Zapus hudsonius [Zimmermann, 1780]. See page 95b.

[2] Currently referred to by the binomial name Lampropeltis triangulum [Lacépède, 1789].

The are two subspecies in Illinois, the nominate Eastern Milksnake (L. t. triangulum) in the north and the Red Milksnake (L. t. syspila) [Cope, 1889] in the south; with integrades existing in the contact zone.

Donations

I am a strong supporter of the Open Access concepts presented by Aaron Swartz (may he never be forgotten) in his Guerilla Open Access Manifesto, including:

“Only those blinded by greed would refuse to let a friend make a copy. Large corporations, of course, are blinded by greed.”

For some people, even charging $1.00 results in a financial access barrier that prevents access to the resource. Those people are not any less worthy than Jeff Bezos or Mark Zuckerberg. This is why this digital book is provided for free without any charge.

That being said, an incredible amount of time, energy, and even some personal financial resources went into the production of this digital book.

I only ask you for $5.00. You can donate more to if you would like, of course, or donate less or even donate none. The choice is completely yours to make and depends upon both your financial means and your personal level of generosity.

Pipfrosch Press

At this time, hopefully soon to be remedied, Pipfrosch Press is not a legal entity. Donations can be made to Michael A. Peters with the understanding that such donations are not at this time tax deductible.

Donations will help Pipfrosch Press continue to produce Open Access digital publications, both the republication of previously print published academic content and the production of fresh content.

To donate using the Android or iOS/iPadOS “CashApp” application:

CashApp tag $AliceWonderMisc

To donate using PayPal:

PayPal Payment Address pipfroschpress@gmail.com. Note that PayPal allows you to make it a monthly donation, only check the box for that if that really is your intention.

Thank you.

Forward

by Michael A. Peters of Pipfrosch Press

The title of this paper is ‘The Quadrupeds of Illinois, Injurious and Beneficial to the Farmer’ but the mammals that it covers are all rodents. Other quadrupeds are not covered. Rumor has it that Robert Kennicott published a few subsequent papers with the same title in subsequent volumes of the Report of the Commissioner of Patents for Agriculture, perhaps this article is the first in a series that alsp cover quadrupeds other than rodents.

While working on a digital publication for the Journal of Mammalogy, Volume 1, Number 2; this paper was cited by one of the authors. As always, I did my best to find the resource cited to verify the works cited section is correct.

The only copy of this paper that I could find in digital form was a very poor quality PDF scan by Google Books: info:hdl/2027/hvd.32044107329120.

My attention was quickly drawn to both the detailed species accounts the author gave and the passion the author had for spreading the message that farmers killing every presumed pest was often a mistake that actually hurts the farmer more than it helps the farmer.

That passion of the author, encouraging an attitude of living in harmony with the natural world as opposed to total domination of the natural world, reminded me of my favorite conservation organization, The Alongside Wildlife Foundation founded by Dr. David A. Steen, and I immediately began transcription of article to the ePub specification.

Even though this article is quite old, it contains a treasure trove of natural history information and much of what is contained within is of benefit both to the naturalist who wants to understand more about the species described within the article as well as to those who wish to farm on the smaller scale in their backyards, a growing trend I wish I had space and resources to partake in myself.

For the young aspiring naturalist, modern academic papers are often very difficult to read due to the high level of academics frequently needed to understand what the author is trying to convey. Older papers, such as this one, can help quench the thirst for knowledge while the aspring naturalist continues to learn what is necessary to properly comprehend modern academic works.

I hope you enjoy reading this paper as much as I did while transcribing it.

Comprehension Tips

It is recommended that before reading this paper, you at least skim the glossary for terms you may not be familiar with.

The author frequently uses the abbreviation ‘&c.’ for ‘Et cetera’. That was common in the 19th century, but it may be unfamiliar to modern readers who are more accustomed to seeing it abbreviated as ‘etc.’

The author often uses the term ‘old male’ where the meaning to be understood is actually adult male.

The author often uses male pronouns where the sex of the subject could be male or female.

The other uses the term ‘arvicolae‘ and ‘meadow-mice‘ interchangeably. He is referring to what we now generally call voles.

This is important to note because from pages 84–90, the author describes the ‘meadow-mice‘ group in general. However the mouse descriptions that directly follow that group description are not voles, and are not considered to be ‘arvicolae‘ or ‘meadow-mice‘ by the author.

It is the opinion of Pipfrosch Press that for clarity, there should have been a different introduction to those mice, but that is not how the article was written.

The actual species accounts to voles (‘arvicolae‘ and ‘meadow-mice‘) do not start until page 97b and happen to specified by the author as belonging to the genus Arvicola. It should be noted that in modern taxonomy, many species formerly placed within Arvicola are now placed within the genus Microtus, including all three species of voles the author gives a species account for.

To summarize, the following species are not what the author considers to be ‘arvicolae‘ or ‘meadow-mice‘ even though they directly follow his description of that group:

Common White-Footed Mouse (White-footed Mouse) on pages 90b–92
White-Footed Prairie Mouse (Deer Mouse) on pages 92b–95
Long-Tailed Jumping Mouse (Meadow Jumping Mouse) on pages 95b–97

Editorial Changes

In the species accounts where the author specified a Name Authority, the author did not include the year of the binomial name description. Those were added.

In the few cases where the author did not include a Name Authority at all, the Name Authority was added with a footnote.

In the one case where the author misspelled the Name Authority, the spelling was corrected.

Pipfrosch Press always places a Name Authority inside square brackets in order to visually distinguish them from other types of references.

Footnotes by the original author are indicated by square brackets around a diamond symbol: [♦].

Footnotes by Pipfrosch Press are indicated by square brackets around a counting number: [1], [2], etc.

The author often capitalized adjectives that were not part of a proper noun. Most of those grammar errors have been fixed to improve readability.

The spelling of some words—such as ‘centre’, ‘grey’, and ‘reconnoitre’—have been updated to use the current American English spellings. I apologize to those who prefer the British spelling, but this paper was originally published in America and already used some Americanized spellings.

The author was very fond of using hyphens. In some cases where the use of hyphens is clearly no longer appropriate in modern typography, those hyphens were removed. There may still be some cases where the excessive use of hyphens can be removed.

With each species account, a taxonomy section was added at the end that gives the current taxonomy nomenclature used, when it differs; as well as the current common name used, when it differs. When available, this section also includes links to more modern resources related to the species that have been kindly provided by the American Society of Mammalogists as Open Access documents. Links to the ITIS TSN report for the species is also provided, and is also a free resource.

When available, quality high resolution color photographs have been added for each species account.

Currently, 8 species accounts are without color photographs and 4 of the existing color photographs I hope to replace in the future.

Grey Prairie-Squirrel

[Plate IX.a]

Spermophilus franklinii [Sabine, 1822]

Description.—Length, about 10 inches from the nose to the root of tail; the tail about 5 inches long. It is a little over three-fourths the size of the migratory squirrel, though its short hair, tail, and legs make it appear smaller; and its form is much thicker and clumsier than that of the true squirrels. The back is light-brown, dotted thickly with black; the under surface is greyish-white. The tail is more bushy than that of the striped spermophile, but much less so, as well as much shorter, than that of the migratory species. It is not so light and active as the striped spermophile, though more so than some of the genus.

The grey prairie squirrel (grey-gopher, of Northern Illinois,) exists throughout the prairie regions of Wisconsin, Illinois, Missouri, Iowa, and probably Minnesota. It is abundant is South-eastern Minnesota, and was observed by Dr. Hoy, in Eastern Kansas. It is also said to exist a great distance to the north and west. It is found much further south in Missouri and Illinois than the Spermophilus tridecemlineatus. It is far less numerous here than the striped spermophile, and appears to be a less abundant species wherever the two exist. It is observed to inhabit the thickets of low bushes, and the edges of the timber, more than the other, but does not occur in the woods. It is fond of digging long burrows in the banks of ditches, and several times, I have seen it living in steep river-banks, as well as under small wooden culverts in roads. It is not so shy as the striped spermophile, and takes up its residence quite near dwellings. It is also less disturbed by the cultivation of land. In this region, it is usually found living alone or in pairs, and I have never observed a number of burrows scattered over a small prairie knoll like the semi-villages of the striped spermophile. This is perhaps owing to their small numbers; for the species appears to be naturally gregarious, and, at times, large companies live together, burrowing within a few feet of each other, and several pairs even entering the same hole.

This spermophile exhibits a remarkable disposition to migrate from one field to another. Not only do the males lead a wandering life in summer, but pairs appear frequently to change their quarters, leaving their winter burrow to breed in another, and then, perhaps, hibernating in a third, at some distance from this. In several instances, a company of a dozen or more have been observed to appear in a locality where none were seen the previous summer, and then to disappear after remaining there a year, or only a few weeks. In the early part of summer, twenty or thirty of these animals suddenly made their appearance, and burrowed in an old embankment within three or four rods of my father’s house. They seemed to have lost the shyness exhibited when leading a solitary life, and were not alarmed at the near approach of man. They even came about the kitchen door to pick up crumbs, and disputed with the chickens for their food. Like the striped spermophiles, they glided silently to their burrows when alarmed, uttering, as they entered, a remarkably clear whistle twitter, more musical than the voice of any other mammal I ever listened to, and as clear as that of a bird. The same note was uttered when the animal was hurt or much frightened. They fed upon June-grass, clover, Timothy, and the broad-leaved plantain, and seemed particularly fond of the leaves of the common mustard, of which some plants grew near their burrows. Other specimens, examined in summer, had their stomachs filled with grass alone. In eating they sat upright on the tarsi, and used their fore-feet as hands, to draw the leaves to their mouths, though their paws were used thus with less facility than those of the true squirrels. Though both the vegetable and flower-garden were situated within five rods of their burrows, I do not remember that they were observed to injure either. A number of young chickens disappearing, however, and the eggs being eaten in several hens’ nests near the burrows of the spermophiles, suspicion rested upon them—probably unjustly—and a war of extermination was commenced. Several were shot while others were killed with clubs, whereupon the survivors left in a body, as suddenly as they had come, and were never seen again, nor could they be found upon any part of the farm. I have known this spermophile to take refuge in a hollow tree, crowding up the hole like the grey-rabbit. Mr. F. C. Sherman, of Chicago, informs me that he twice saw one, when pursued, climb five or six feet up the trellis-work and vines at the side of a house.

The burrow of this species is usually deeper than that of the striped spermophile, but otherwise similar to it. The young, I have not observed, but Mr. George S. Parker, of Pecatonica, Illinois, writes me that he once saw five, and at another time seven young in a nest. They appear to go into winter-quarters in the fall, and re-appear in the spring, at about the same time as the striped spermophile. They have been found hibernating under piles of rails, and in corn-shocks; and I am informed of two instances in which one has been found torpid in a hay-stack, where he had formed a burrow in the hay. I have never heard of its hibernating in such situations. A caged specimen of Franklin’s spermophile, kept by Professor Baird, of the Smithsonian Institution, was active all winter; and Dr. A. M. D. Hughes, of Payson, Illinois, informs me that he found one in a burrow under a corn-shock, active in mild weather, late in November.

This species is carnivorous , though apparently less so than the striped spermophile. The specimen kept by Professor Baird was decidedly carnivorous, but one observed by Dr. Hoy did not eat mice, though it killed them when placed in its cage. Its food is generally similar to that of the striped spermophile, stores being also found in its burrow. It gnaws hard substances more than the striped spermophile, and, while the latter will not gnaw out of a box, this readily does so. Caged specimens cut open hazel-nuts also.

This squirrel injures the farmer by taking up newly-planted corn as does the striped spermophile. Being far less abundant than the other, however, it is usually less complained of on newly-broken land; but it is sometimes the more injurious of the two on old farms, where it burrows in cultivated fields more willingly than the other. It frequently burrows during summer in grain-fields, where it eats the green plants, and afterwards the heads of grain as the kernels fill; and in this manner, and by throwing down the standing grain, spoils it for some distance around the burrow. Having a great predilection for burrowing in ditch banks, and in under drains filled with brush, it often does serious injury in this way.

This species may be destroyed in the same manner as the preceding, though they are not so easily drowned out of their holes, especially when they are in a bank or drain. They appear to leave their burrows with less caution, and for a greater distance, than the others; and, being also left active, they are sometimes chased and killed with a stick. They are probably more liable to the attacks of rapacious animals than the others. I have known domestic cats to catch them, when full-grown.

It is possible that the striped spermophile drives off this species, as the two are not found occupying the same field.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

In 2009, this subgenus Poliocitellus was elevated to full genus status resulting in the binomial name Poliocitellus franklinii [Sabine, 1822] for this species.

This species is currently referred to using the common name Franklin’s Ground Squirrel.

For more information on the current taxonomy of the Thirteen-Lined Ground Squirrel, see:

Generic Revision in the Holarctic Ground Squirrel Genus Spermophilus (Helgen, 2009): DOI:10.1644/07-MAMM-A-309.1
ITIS Report for TSN 930309

Wood-Chuck, or Ground-Hog

[Plate X.a, Photo 13]

Arctomys monax [Linnæus, 1758]

Description.—The wood-chuck is about 18 inches in length from the nose to the root of the tail, with the vertebrae of the tail about 4 inches. The tail is bushy, but small; the ears and legs short; the body thick and heavy; a full-sized specimen weighing 9 or 10 pounds. The usual color of the back is grizzly-brown, with the head, tail and feet darker; the belly reddish.

The wood-chuck is familiar to the farmers of the Eastern and Middle States. It is abundant on the Missouri River, and exists westward to the Rocky Mountains. Northward, it is found as far as Hudson’s Bay. In this part of Illinois, it was exceedingly rare ten years ago, but is now becoming quite common. It is an inhabitant of the woods, where it occupies the place that the spermophiles do on the prairies; and, though it burrows in open fields, and in the timber, I am not aware that it ever lives on the prairie, though I have seen it in the prairie groves. At the East, it inhabits open fields in preference to the deep woods. This love for open ground is probably acquired. Here, I have most commonly observed it in the heaviest timber, and it is said to be found most abundantly in wood-lands in Missouri. It digs its burrow under a log, brush-heap, or fence, or among rocks; and particularly delights in rocky bluffs. River-banks are also its favorite resorts. At the East, dry pastures and meadows are frequented, where it likes to dig its burrow under a fence or stone-wall, with an opening on each side.

This animal is fond of clover; and where it abounds, a clover meadow is sure to be occupied by it, sometimes to the no small damage of the crop, which it injures by treading it down around the burrow. It is also very fond of peas, and never fails to visit a pea-field situated near its retreat. Corn and other grain are sometimes pulled down and eaten by it. It is, however, only near the burrows that it is seriously injurious, as, like the spermophiles, it leaves these with great caution, and only for a short distance.

When surprised away from home, this species always attempts to retreat to its hole, running or moving by short and awkward jumps, made apparently with much effort. It manages to get over the ground with greater speed than might be expected, considering its form, though a man can outrun one in a race by several rods. It is very watchful, and, when feeding, will frequently stand erect, with the neck stretched as high as possible, and look suspiciously about. It usually stands on the hind-feet, in feeding, as it frequently does at other times.

From four to six young are produced each season. These are brought forth in the early part of summer, and, before fall, leave the mother, to dig their own burrows and shift for themselves. The female exhibits considerable affection for her young, and seldom deserts them when in danger. The old males appear to lead a solitary life, in summer, like the spermophiles, leaving the family den to the female and young. Only a single pair of adults occupy the same burrow. The hibernation of the wood-chuck is as profound as that of the spermophiles. Naturally, this animal is strictly herbivorous. Though living in the woods, it does not eat nuts, nor gnaw bark, nor am I aware that it ever digs roots. It is not a tree climber, though it sometimes crawls up a leaning tree, or into the thick branches of bushes overgrown with vines, on which it is fond of lying in warm sunny days. In this vicinity, I have often found a number of them taking refuge in standing hollow trees, entering a hole at the ground, and climbing up the cavity in the manner of the grey-rabbit.

When fat, which they usually are in autumn, wood-chucks are esteemed by some as good eating, if properly cooked. They are sometimes baked whole, or are better, if parboiled in milk, and afterwards “potted down.”

The fur of this animal is of no value, but the dressed hide is very tough, and highly esteemed among the back-woodsmen for making whip-lashes, money-pouches, and various other articles of use.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

When Linnæus described this species, he named it Mus monax, placing it in the genus Mus, a sort of taxonomy dumping ground where he placed most rodents he described, figuring—correctly so—that it would get sorted out later.

In 1780 Schreber defined the genus Arctomys using this species as the type species for the genus, resulting in the binomial nomenclature Arctomys monax used by the author of this article.

Most of the species (but not all) that Schreber and others put into Arctomys actually align with the genus Marmota [Blumenbach, 1779; TSN 180136], described just a year prior. As the Arctomys type species Arctomys monax is one of the species that aligns with Marmota, the genus Arctomys is now considered to be a junior synonym of Marmota.

Marmota monax [Linnæus, 1758] is the currently accepted binomial nomenclature for this species.

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Groundhog’.

For more information on the Groundhog, see:

Mammalian Species № 591: DOI:10.2307/3504364
ITIS Report for TSN 180137

Large-Tailed Fox-Squirrel

[Plate V.a]

Sciurus magnicaudatus [Harlan, 1825]
Sciurus macrourus [Say and Godman, 1823]
Sciurus sayi, and S. rubricaudatus [Audubon and Bachman, 1851]

Description.—Form of large female in winter much stouter and heavier than that of the Sciurus migratorius; length from snout to root of tail, 12 inches; tail, (vertebræ,) 10½ inches; tail to end of longest hair, 14 inches; hind-foot from heel to longest toe, 3 inches; breadth of head between ears, 1¾ inches; girth behind the shoulders, 7 inches; weight, 2 pounds and 2 ounces; breadth across the tail, with the hairs in their natural position, as in life, 6 inches. The outside of the ear is clothed with long hairs, which extend over three-eighths of an inch beyond the tip. The rudimental thumb of the fore-foot is protected by a flat, blunt nail. In this, as in other winter specimens of this species, the coat of fur is remarkably thick and warm.

The general color of the fox-squirrel is mixed, grey and black above and reddish yellow below; the hairs on the back are bluish-black at the base, broadly ringed with brown, more narrowly with black, then with greyish-white, and slightly tipped with black; a few hairs extend beyond the rest, the extra length of these being entirely black. The hairs on the top of the tail have three black and three light - brown rings alternately , broadly tipped with reddish-yellow. On the sides and tip of the tail, the hairs are for two thirds of their length reddish-yellow, then ringed once more with black, and broadly tipped with darker reddish-yellow; on the under surface of the tail, the hairs are entirely of a bright reddish-yellow. Thus the under side of the tail is of a deep reddish-yellow, surrounded by a distinct subterminal band of black, beyond which it is edged with the color of the center; the upper surface of the tail is mixed, brown and black, beautifully edged with a terminal band of reddish-yellow. The cheeks, upper lips, the space around the eyes, ears, feet, and entire under parts of the body and legs are of a rich reddish-yellow. The hairs on the belly are ashen for a short distance at the base. The whiskers are entirely black. The toes and soles of the feet are also black; nails black tipped with white; incisors deep reddish orange. One remarkable feature in this species is that the bones are tinged with red. Summer specimens are of lighter colors, with the hair much thinner and shorter, and without the thick coat of long hair on the posterior surface of the ear.

With one exception, I have seen no distinct varieties of color in this species. In some specimens, at different seasons, the color of the underparts, however, grades from light-yellow to deep reddish-orange; and a summer specimen, obtained in Missouri by Dr. P. R. Hoy, of Racine, Wisconsin, has the under parts of a dark-rufous cast. This specimen is also blacker than usual on the back, and comes nearer to Audobon and Bachman’s figure of S. sayi than any other I have seen. This and other specimens of the two extremes of coloring in other respects are alike.

A variety of this species is occasionally met with in which the tail and upper parts are of the usual colors, but with the entire under parts of the body perfectly black. It has only been observed in Southern Wisconsin and Northern Illinois.

I have thus minutely described this squirrel because Audubon and Bachman have, in their “Quadrupeds of North America,” made two species of it. It is undoubtedly the S. magnicaudatus, of Harlan, first described by Say, who unfortunately gave it a name already belonging to another squirrel. Under the name of S. sayi, Audubon and Bachman have described a specimen of this species, of unusually bright colors, their highly-colored figure exaggerating the hue of the under parts to a bright orange-red, or ferruginous. This they give as the “Great-tailed Squirrel” of Say, Godman, and Harlan, and as being an abundant species in Illinois. But, among hundreds of specimens both from Northern and Southern Illinois, as well as from Michigan, Indiana, and Wisconsin, examined in the Chicago markets and elsewhere, I never saw one corresponding fully to the figure and description of S. sayi given by the authors named above. The figure and description of their S. rubricaudatus, were taken from a young specimen of this species in summer pelage of rather light color.

In its home at the West, this large and beautiful species is universally known under the name of “Fox-squirrel,” and, though other American species are also called by this name, it would be useless now to attempt to apply another. This squirrel has been observed throughout Illinois, in Southern Wisconsin, Eastern Iowa, Southern Michigan, Western Indiana, and, according to Dr. Hoy, throughout the northern part of Missouri, as far as the Osage River, at least, and in Eastern Kansas. I have also seen it from Western Kentucky, where I am informed it abounds, as well as in Southeastern Missouri, and it will probably be found in other States further to the south and west. Captain Marcy saw a species he supposed to be the S. magnicaudatus as far south as the Red River of Louisiana. In Northern Michigan, Northern Wisconsin, Northern Iowa, and in Minnesota , I am informed it does not exist, and its northern limit appears to be between the forty-third and forty-fifth parallels of north latitude, though further north it is said to be found in Eastern Michigan. Several specimens of this species have been seen in Ohio, but their appearance is explained by the fact that several individuals taken in Wisconsin, are known to have been liberated in the same locality, some time before. It is very abundant throughout Illinois, where, in some localities, it exists in greater numbers than any other species.

The fox-squirrel loves neither low lands nor deep woods; and, though found living in the heavily-timbered districts of Indiana and Illinois, it is less at home in these than in more open ground. It is properly an inhabitant of the timber of the prairie regions, and its favorite habitat is in the “oak openings” of Wisconsin and Michigan, and the groves or edges of the belts of timber that skirt the streams watering the prairies of Illinois. Since these river belts and the prairie groves, or “Islands,” as the old settlers appropriately termed them, have been protected from the fires that formerly swept them annually, many young trees, especially pin-oak (Quercus palustris), in Northern Illinois have sprung up around them at the edges of the prairie, forming ornamental clumps, that are useful as protection against the sharp prairie winds—the more so as the pin-oak retains its leaves during winter. These are favorite haunts of the fox-squirrel, and whenever a hollow tree of larger size stands in one of these outlaying groves, it will be the home of a pair. In some localities in Northern Illinois, many young pin-oaks are destroyed by having the bark stripped from the trunks and larger branches which kills the tops. As neither the porcupine nor any other bark-eating mammal which can climb, is found here, and as this squirrel is known to frequent these young pin-oaks, the guilt has been charged upon him without further evidence than this. It is only within a few years that this extensive destruction of the young oaks has been observed in this vicinity, and it is yearly increasing, while the fox-squirrels are now less numerous than formerly, and food is more abundant, as hogs do not now consume the mast as they did several years ago. Though the tops of hundreds of trees have thus been killed. I have observed none gnawed in neighboring woods where the fox-squirrels are equally numerous.

If this bark-gnawing increases and becomes general in this vicinity, it will be a source of much damage, as the blighted tops of the injured trees would sadly disfigure our beautiful prairie islands in summer. To eat bark, would be a departure from the natural habits of this animal, and, before the guilt of being the author of this mischief can be justly fixed upon him, better proof must be produced. It is not impossible that some bark-gnawing rodent, hitherto unnoticed, may exist here.

But the fox-squirrel is also charged with thieving from the corn-field; and this accusation is supported by unimpeachable evidence. More corn is destroyed by this species than is usually supposed, the mischief being, without investigation, very generally charged upon the raccoons. But any of our farmers, whose corn-fields are situated in or adjoining to timber, inhabited by it, will find that, while the corn is in milk, many ears are opened, and, if not eaten, much injured, or destroyed, by exposure to the weather. The small-sized marks of the squirrel’s cutting teeth in the husks, instead of those made by the raccoon’s widely-separated canines, and the fact that the corn is not torn down as it would be by a heavy animal, will sufficiently prove to him that it is not the raccoon, alone, which does the mischief. And, if he will watch carefully some day in his corn-field, he will detect more than one red bushy tail, whisked incessantly up and down, as its owner, clinging to a corn-stalk, makes a delicious meal of the milky grains. Not only does he thus eat the corn on the stalk, but he gnaws off whole ears, which are never eaten on the ground, but always carried to the fence, or to a neighboring tree, where, perched upon a flat rail or large limb, he discusses them at his leisure. Sitting upon his hind-feet, he tears off the husk and pulls out the kernels with his teeth; and, if the corn is in the milk, all the soft part is eaten, but, when ripened, he often lays down the ear, and holding the kernels in his paws, only gnaws out the germ. Along fences, or under trees, situated in or near corn-fields thus attacked by squirrels, husks, cobs, and partly-eaten ears of corn may frequently be found. Sometimes, when squirrels are molested, they do not stay near the field to eat the corn, but carry the ears off to some distance in the woods. I am informed that when the crop of mast is scanty, large corn fields have been destroyed in parts of Illinois and Indiana by this, and one or the other of the two species next to be described; while fields in these localities are more or less injured every year, especially if bordered by timber, or with a few old trees standing in them, in which the squirrels can take refuge, as they venture with less fear into these fields than into those at a distance from their congenial refuge. I have observed, however, that the fox-squirrel will leave the immediate vicinity of trees more readily than the other species. Like other squirrels, it will run along fence to a much greater distance from the woods than it will travel on the ground; and, when in the woods, it will always run upon a log in preference to keeping upon the ground.

This, as well as several other true squirrels, will sometimes, though rarely, dig up newly-planted corn; and at times it devours wheat and also other grain. But, usually, the only considerable injury it does the farmer is in the destruction of corn in the ear.

In the woods, the food of the fox-squirrel consists almost entirely of the nuts and seeds of trees, with the buds of some species, including bass-wood, elm, and maple. In autumn, it eats the fruit of various thorns (cratægus); various berries are also eaten by it, and it is said to be particularly fond of strawberries. In common with other squirrels, it sometimes eats insects; and it has occasionally been observed to gnaw the bark from dead trees, to procure beetles and their larvæ. Like other squirrels, too, it has been seen to gnaw through the bark of trees girdled in spring, to taste the decomposing sap. So fond of this is it that fifteen or twenty [Sic] grey-squirrels have been seen thus engaged upon a single oak, thus girdled.

It is a common opinion that this and other squirrels carry large hoards of nuts to hollow trees for consumption in winter. So far as our three species, common in Illinois are concerned, this is entirely erroneous. With the exception of the little “Chickaree,” no true squirrel that I have observed ever collects food for winter in hollow trees. A few nut shells are sometimes found in a squirrel’s hole, but these are only such as he has taken there to be eaten at the time. The fox-squirrel, with the migratory and Carolina squirrels, also, as well as others probably, buries large quantities of nuts and acorns under the leaves in autumn, for use in winter. These, however, are not collected together, but concealed one in a place. In winter, the squirrels dig them up; and, when the ground is covered with snow, numerous holes will be seen where they have dug down to get them. It is interesting to notice that they seldom dig through the snow and leaves in this way without coming directly upon the buried nut or acorn, and a common idea is that the animal “remembers” the spot. This is highly improbable. It is more reasonable to suppose that the animal is guided by the sense of smell. Dr. Hoy tells me that he has seen squirrels run about with the nose close to the snow or leaves, and finally dig directly upon a buried nut without hesitation. He gives it as his opinion that they can always smell the food, unless it is buried under very deep snow. I am not aware that corn is thus stored for winter use. Though many nuts and acorns are buried in this way, the fox squirrel, as observed in Northern Illinois, at least, does not depend much upon them for food, when the snow is deep, at which time it feeds chiefly upon buds, searching carefully, also, for the few nuts, acorns, and seeds which may have remained upon the trees, and for the dry berries of the Celastrus scandens, and other vines or shrubs.

Mr. Smiley Shepherd, of Hennepin, Illinois, in a letter containing reliable account of the mammals of his region, informs me that he has repeatedly observed where the fox-squirrels have carried large numbers of nuts and deposited them securely in the forks of small trees, their tracks being readily traced in the snow to where the nuts had been recently dug out. This was observed in cold weather, when the snow was deep. Unless Mr. Shepherd mistook the work of wood-peckers and nut-hatches for that of squirrels—which is hardly probable—this is an interesting fact with regard to the habits of this squirrel.

I have observed that, in digging nuts from under the leaves, in winter, the fox-squirrel never remains upon the ground to eat them, but carries them to a neighboring stump or log, or, more frequently, to the low branches of some small tree, under which the shells are found cut and broken into a number of pieces, instead of having small linear openings cut through the thinnest part of the shell.

The fox-squirrel is more solitary in its habits than the migratory squirrel. More than two old ones are rarely, if ever, found living together. In the summer and fall, the old males lead a solitary life, as they sometimes do in winter. As soon as the young are able to take care of themselves, the female usually drives them off, when the old male, which has retired to a summer residence to escape the discomfort attendant upon the rearing of a family, returns to the winter-quarters and society of his chosen mate; for, usually, this species is not polygamous. This squirrel often, if not generally, builds several nests, each of which is sometimes a simple pile of twigs and leaves placed in the forks of a tree, but at other times is carefully and ingeniously constructed, being round, with the central cavity quite roofed over, and a small entrance on one side. The more carefully-formed nests are usually on tall trees, but temporary habitations are frequently built on small trees, and within 20 feet of the ground. After being driven off by the mother, the young usually separate and lead a wandering life, for a time, at least. They build nests wherever they stop, even for a day or two; and I have several times observed individuals to appear in a grove of young oaks, build a nest, remain a few days, and then disappear, perhaps to return again in a week and build other nests.

The fox-squirrel loves to take up his abode in a hollow tree which stands out alone at a little distance from the surrounding timber, as if desirous of having a clear view of all going on around him. When he once becomes domiciled in a tree, he does not leave it, unless disturbed, pairs being observed to inhabit the same tree for five or six successive years. It is less prolific than either the migratory or Carolina squirrel. From two to four young are usually brought forth at a birth, the most common number being three; but in one instance, I have seen five. Two litters are probably produced each season. So far as has been observed, they are always brought forth in the hole, the nests of leaves being only used as summer-houses. Like the young of most rodents, they are ugly, unsymmetrical little beings, at first, with monstrous heads and closed eyes; and it is some time before they acquire the elegant proportions and agile movements of their parents.

These squirrels sometimes leave their holes for food, and even for amusement, in very cold and rainy weather, when they are found moving about much more than the migratory species. But, though active at this time and apparently engaged in play, they do not now “bark,” as on warm and pleasant days. Like other squirrels they dislike to move about in windy weather, when the waving branches make their highways among the tree-tops insecure.

The old comparison, “As lively as a squirrel,” is not inapt, and the fox-squirrel, like the other, exhibits remarkably active habits. While the females and young are together, in early autumn, it is amusing to watch the movements of a party on any pleasant day, when their enjoyment of the abundant food and things in general is testified by a degree of sprightliness and agility quite astonishing. One afternoon, in September, by concealing myself near a large hickory on which four or five were engaged in eating unripe nuts, I had an opportunity of witnessing their movements without alarming them. With surprising ease, one would run out upon a limb so slender that it would bend beneath his weight, and, seizing a nut in his teeth, he would pull it off and carry it back to a more secure seat on a large branch, always returning to the same spot. Here, standing upon his hind-feet in a posture nearly erect, and holding the nut in his fore-paws, he first gnawed off the outer covering, and then cut open the shell and devoured the kernel rapidly. Sometimes, in attempting to pick a nut, one would drop it, when he would invariably stop, turn his head on one side, and, with a provokingly comical expression, watch its descent. They seldom remained quiet for a minute at a time. If not eating, they would scamper up and down, sometimes springing from limb to limb, with no other apparent object than fun. Their long bushy tails were never kept still, but continually jerked up and down. Occasionally, one would stop for an instant, and utter a short bark, or chatter. One kept aloof from the rest, and when approached by any of them in their play, chased them off with an angry gutteral snarl. A movement at length discovering me to them, some scampered further up the tree, while one, after watching my partly-concealed form a moment, ran down the trunk to within 20 feet of the ground and, spreading himself out flat against the tree, with his head down and tail extended straight behind him, barked at me with energy. He first uttered several abrupt notes, quak-quak—and then a long shrill qua’a-a-a, the number of the short sounds varying, but always followed by the long sharp qua’a-a-a. At the repitition of each short note, he jerked his body violently, and whisked up his tail slightly, giving it a gracefully undulating motion. He continued to bark thus incessantly for several minutes, until, at length, I exposed myself fully to view, when he hastened to the opposite side of the tree, and ran to the top, uttering a low chatter of affright.

This species is usually more silent than the migratory squirrel; and, if one of them hears any loud noise in the woods, it hides or runs to its hole, instead of chattering at it, as the other often will; though, while at work in a field near the summer home of an old male, I have many a day been cheered by his merry quak-quck-qua’a-a-a, uttered for an hour at a time.

To use the words of the hunters, fox-squirrels “hole” more than the migratory squirrels; that is, they keep more in holes, spending less time in their nests of leaves, to which, however, they are fond of retiring on sunny days late in autumn. At this time, I have seen lazy hunters go about firing into the nests with shot guns, calculating that the proportion containing squirrels would compensate for the waste of ammunition fired at empty nests.

I am not aware that this species has ever been known to migrate in large companies, though some will occasionally move from place to place singly, in search of food, as will the Carolina squirrel and several others, besides the migratory squirrel. Several instances are on record of a fox-squirrel crossing a prairie in summer four or five miles in width, to reach timber upon the other side.

This species, as if from living in more open woods, runs better upon the ground than others. They venture a considerable distance from their home, but when chased, they will even, if hard pressed, run a long way upon the ground in the endeavor to reach their hole, rather than take to the first tree, like other squirrels. The tree attained, they never stop upon its branches, but run directly into the hole. In the woods this squirrel is usually more shy than any others that I have observed; at least, it will not expose itself as boldly to any one seen by it. Yet it takes up its abode near dwellings much oftener than the others; indeed, I know of no squirrel, excepting perhaps the chickaree, that will live as near the habitations of man as this. I have observed several instances in which pairs of fox-squirrels have lived and reared young, for a number of years, in trees situated within a few rods[1] of dwelling-houses; and, in winter, I have seen these, as well as others from the woods, come boldly about the farm-yard or corn-crib in search of food.

For a figure of the fox-squirrel, (S. cinereus), of Pensylvania, see Plate V.b.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

At the beginning of this species section, the author references four binomial names in use at the time for the species being referenced.

The author notes that both Sciurus sayi and Sciurus rubricaudatus (both [Audubon and Bachman, 1851]) are junior synonyms to Sciurus magnicaudatus [Harlan, 1825]. The author further mentions that Sciurus macrourus [Say and Goodman, 1823] is an invalid senior synonym to Sciurus magnicaudatus, leaving S. magnicaudatus as the binomial nomenclature the author accepts.

The author further distinguishes the subject of this species section from Sciurus cinereus [Linnæus, 1758] as two distinct species.

In Mammalian Species № 479 (published by the American Society of Mammalogists in 1994) both Sciurus magnicaudatus and Sciurus cinereus are listed as a junior synomyns to the binomial Sciurus niger [Linnæus, 1758], with S. magnicaudatus now a junior synonym to the subspecies trinomial Sciurus niger rufiventer [St.-Hilaire, 1803] and S. cinereus now a synonym to the subspecies trinomial Sciurus niger cinereus.

For more information on the current taxonomy of the Large-Tailed Fox-Squirrel, see:

Mammalian Species № 479: DOI:10.2307/3504263
ITIS Report for TSN 930496

[1] A rod is approximately five meters.

Little Red-Squirrel

[Plate VII.a]

Sciurus hudsonicus [Erxleben, 1777][1]

Description.—Length of adult male in winter, from nose to root of tail, 8¼ inches; tail, (vertebræ,) 5⅛ inches; tail to end of hair, 6¾ inches; hind-foot, 1⅞ inches; breadth of tail with the hair in natural position, 1½ inches; back, light greyish-brown, with a dorsal stripe of bright reddish-brown; tail, bright reddish-brown above, dingy-brown below, with a subterminal border of black; under parts of head and body, pure white. This is full a third smaller than the migratory squirrel; the hairs clothing the body are much shorter, and the tail less bushy. There are no distinct varieties though the colors of the upper parts are sometimes—if not generally, at the East—much redder than in the specimen here described, being without the dorsal stripe of a color so different from that of the rest of the back. Other specimens from Ohio are colored like that described.

This pretty and active little animal is well known through the Northern States, under the names of “Red-Squirrel,” “Chickaree,” “Pine Squirrel,” and, sometimes, “Mountain Squirrel.“ It is a Northern species, but has a wide geographical range. It is found abundantly throughout the Eastern and Middle States, and probably exists as far to the northward as the pine and spruce occur. Southward, in the Atlantic States, it is found in the mountains of Virginia, and, according to Audubon and Bachman, it has even been seen within North Carolina. In the interior, it abounds in Ohio and Indiana, and is found sparingly in heavy timber in Illinois; but it is not common, if it occurs at all, in the southern parts of these States. West of the Mississippi, it has rarely been seen in Northern Missouri. It is found in Central Iowa, and is abundant in parts of Southeastern Minnesota, where, in fact, it is the only species. About Lake Superior, in Northern Minnesota and Wisconsin, where no other squirrel prevails, it is found in exceeding abundance. It probably exists further to the west, but on the other side of the Rocky Mountains it is replaced by other small species closely resembling it.

The natural home of this squirrel is in heavy timber on high land. It is not found in the small, sparsely-timbered prairie groves, nor in the oak openings. It loves to take up its residence among evergreens, the cones of which form its favorite food, those of the black-spruce particularly. In cultivated districts, it sometimes departs from its natural habits. It becomes accustomed to man’s presence, living sometimes in trees quite near dwellings, and frequently in out-houses, in winter, when it comes fearlessly about the house and corn-crib. It is attached to its home, and will not leave its favorite tree unless much molested.

Unlike any other of the true squirrels found here, this species sometimes, but not generally, lives in holes in the ground. Unlike the others, too, it collects into its hole in autumn an ample provision of the good things of squirrel life, wherewith to console and sustain itself in the uncomfortable season of frost and snow. It is well known that the chickaree makes large hoards of nuts, acorns, and seeds. These are deposited in hollow trees, and sometimes under fallen logs, and even occasionally in holes in the ground. In consequence of his good cheer, this squirrel is seen actively scampering about in cold weather, when his hungry cousins cannot pluck up courage to leave their warm abodes, even in search of food. In the corn-field, his depredations are at times the source of much annoyance to the farmer. Besides eating at the time with others, this provident species is said to carry off corn to its hole for winter use.

The red-squirrel runs with great swiftness; and though it cannot leap as far as the migratory species, it darts along the trunk of a tree much more rapidly. Its note is a merry, shrill chir-r-r-r-r, very unlike the “bark” of the migratory and fox squirrels.

Like the red-fox and some other animals, this squirrel appears in some instances to follow the settlements of the white man. In parts of Northern Illinois, where it was not seen formerly, it is now occasionally found, and is increasing in numbers. Dr. Kirtland speaks of it as having scarecely made its appearance, about the beginning of the present century, on the Western Reserve, in Ohio, where it is now exceedingly abundant. It may be, however, that this appearance of the red squirrels in these localities, is the result of the destruction of certain enemies. It is very certain that they were abundant further to the west and north, before any settlements were made there.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

In Mammalian Species № 586 (published by the American Society of Mammalogists in 1998) Sciurus hudsonicus is listed as a synonym for Tamiasciurus hudsonicus [Erxleben, 1777] indicating this species has been moved out of the genus Sciurus. There are numerous described subspecies.

For more information on the current taxonomy of the Little Red-Squirrel, see:

Mammalian Species № 586: DOI:10.2307/3504443
ITIS Report for TSN 180166

[1] The author gave an incorrect spelling of Sciurus hudsonius using the authority [Pennant]. Pennant did describe the species but did not give it a specific name, Erxleben assigned the specific name using the description by Pennant for the type. The mispelling used by the author was also used by Gmelin in 1788 and may be where the author got his spelling.

The correct spelling of Sciurus hudsonicus with the correct authority [Erxleben, 1777] is used in the article in place of the mistake.

Long-Haired Meadow-Mouse

pages 104b–105

[Plate XIII.a, Plate XIII.b, Photo 19]

Arvicola riparius [Ord, 1825][1]

Description.—Length of head and body of the male in spring, 4 inches; tail, (vertebrae,) 1 inch; hind-foot, ⅞ of an inch. The general color of the upper parts resembles that of Arvicola austerus, but there is no black tip to the tail. The belly and under part of the tail are grayish-white. The incisors are bright-orange. The fur on the back, as well as on the belly, is much thicker and longer than that of the Arvicola austerus. This species may readily be distinguished from the preceding, by the different color of the teeth and under parts, and the much longer tail and fur. The color of the back varies sometimes, as it does in a specimen for which I am indebted to Professor A. Winchell, of the Michigan University, the back of which is of a rusty brown color; and Dr. Hoy informs me that he has seen specimens with similar coloring.

This meadow-mouse abounds in Northern Illinois and Southern Wisconsin, and has been taken in Michigan. Dr. Hoy informs me that he met with a few specimens near Lexington, in Lafayette county, Missouri. The Arvicola riparius is far less abundant in this vicinity than the preceding. Among twenty or thirty specimens of the Arvicola austerus, taken in various localities in the fields and on the prairies, in autumn, there were but two or three of this species. Dr. Hoy informs me that, near Racine, they abound in meadows, in the woods, burrowing under stumps and trees, in situations never inhabited by the Arvicola austerus, as well as on the prairies; but, so far as has been observed, this species does not inhabit heavy timber. It appears to be a prairie animal, though sometimes found thus living in timber-lands. Inhabiting both high and low-land, yet it shows no preference for wet places, as does the species last described. It is not numerous in fields in which the Arvicola austerus abounds, though existing in the greatest abundance elsewhere. Considering this, and the greater strength and pugnacity of the Arvicola austerus, it seems probable that the latter drives it off. The burrow of this species is very different from that of the preceding, being simple and of slight extent. It appears also to be more gregarious. I have, indeed, several times found a half dozen or more inhabiting the same corn shock or potato heap.

In captivity, this animal is less pugnacious than the Arvicola austerus; but it is much more noisy also, crying out almost continually, when several are eating together, or at all disturbed. The voice is a harsh creaking squeal. The food and habits, so far as observed, are, with the exceptions mentioned, the same in this as in the preceding species.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

Arvicola riparius [Ord, 1825] is now considered to be a junior synonym of Microtus pennsylvanicus [Ord, 1815]. Several subspecies are described, Illinois falls within the range of the nominate subspecies M. p. pennsylvanicus [Ord, 1815] although many no longer recognize the validity of any subspecies within M. pennsylvanicus.

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Meadow Vole’.

For more information on the Meadow Vole, see:

Mammalian Species № 159: DOI:10.2307/3503976
ITIS Report for TSN 180297

[1] The author did not specify the authority for Arvicola riparius. The correct authority of [Ord, 1825] has been added.

Long-Tailed Jumping Mouse

[Plate XI.b]

Jaculus labradorius [Kerr, 1792]

Description.—This Jaculus labradorius, with several allied species, differs materially from the true mice in form and habits. It is about 2½ inches long, with the tail often twice that length, and always much longer than the body; the hind-foot, from the heel to the end of the longest toe, is nearly 2 inches. At the tip of the tail is usually a pencil of long hairs, though this is wanting in some specimens. The body is of a dark-brown above, yellowish-brown on the sides, and white, or at times rusty-white, on the under surface. The fore-legs are small; but the hind-tarsi are very long, with the legs and thighs large and muscular; which peculiar structure enables this little animal to take leaps of almost incredible length. It travels in this way so rapidly that a man must run fast to overtake it. I am informed that, when alarmed, it has been seen to spring 8 or 10 feet at once. At times it travels by these long leaps, when not disturbed; but it may also be seen walking or running on all four feet.

This animal is known as the “Long-tailed Deer Mouse,” “Fob-tailed Mouse,” “Kangaroo Mouse,” “Jumping Mouse,” “Buck Mouse,” “Wood Mouse,” and other names, common also to the Mus leucopus[1], from which it is usually distinguished by the prefix of “long-tailed,” or “jumping.” It exists probably in the entire northern part of the United States, as well as further to the northward. In this vicinity, it is a much less abundant species than the Mus leucopus. It is not very prolific, and is nowhere numerous. In Northern Illinois, it is found in the deepest woods, as well as in cultivated fields, and on the prairie at a distance from any timber. In the woods, it is often found nesting in situations similar to those occupied by Mus leucopus. It cannot climb, but crawls up the inside of hollow trees to a considerable height from the ground, and is sometimes found nesting in them; but its nest is often discovered under the bark of rotten trees or stumps; and, though not much noticed when inhabiting these situations, it appears frequently, if not generally, to live in burrows in the ground, as it nearly always does in the fields, and on the prairies, of course. It digs readily. Its burrow in summer is not deep, and the nest is sometimes found in a tuft of grass above the surface, or under an inverted sod. In cultivated fields, it lives under fences, and, like the mice and arvicolæ, takes up its abode in grain that has been cut and left standing out.

The food of this species appears to consist chiefly of herbaceous plants, with their seeds, and the seeds and nuts of trees, when it inhabits the woods. In cultivated fields, it devours grain, of which it has sometimes been observed to collect stores in its burrows. But it does not appear to be very injurious to the farmer; and, as it produces but few young, and has numerous enemies, it will probably never increase so as to become a source of serious damage.

The jumping mouse is so generally confounded with the Mus leucopus that its habits are seldom correctly known among farmers. It is commonly believed to be active in winter, laying up a store of provisions in autumn for consumption at that time. Nuts, grain, and seeds, indeed, are found in its burrows, but they are collected, apparently, at all seasons, as in the case of the prairie-squirrels. That this animal hibernates is certain. Godman says that, “at the commencement of cool weather, or about the time the frost sets in, the jumping mice go into their winter-quarters, where they remain in a torpid state.” Dr. Hoy informs me that, when he was a boy, in digging out a rabbit in winter, he found a pair of this species in a state of profound torpor, exhibiting all the phenomena of perfect hibernation. They were in a large nest of leaves situated two or three feet below the surface. Audubon and Bachman, ignoring the statement of Godman, say it is doubtful whether this species hibernates. But the observations of so reliable a naturalist as Dr. Hoy are enough to settle the question, even if we discredit Godman’s statement, which I see no sufficient reason for doing.

The jumping mouse is nocturnal, but may be regarded as less completely so than the white-footed mouse, as it has been occasionally seen moving out voluntarily by day. It produces only from two to four young at a birth, and, being a hibernating animal, probably not over one or two litters in a year.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The author neglected to specify an authority for the binomial name Jaculus labradorius.

Given both the specific name and the description the author gives, he is almost certainly referencing Dipus labradorius [Kerr, 1792; TSN 952140] which is now considered to be a junior synonym of Zapus hudsonius [Zimmermann, 1780]. Several subspecies are described, Illinois falls within the range of the nominate subspecies Z. h. hudsonius [Zimmermann, 1780].

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Meadow Jumping Mouse’.

For more information on the Meadow Jumping Mouse, see:

Mammalian Species № 11: DOI:10.2307/3504066
ITIS Report for TSN 180386

[1] Currently referred to by the binomial name Peromyscus leucopus [Rafinesque, 1818].

Meadow-Mice

Of Meadow-mice, we have many species, some being found in nearly every part of the United States. They all resemble each other; and, where several species are found in one locality, they are commonly considered by farmers as one animal, known under various names, as “Short-tailed Field Rats or Mice,” “Bear Mice,” “Bull-headed Mice,” “Ground Mice,” “Bog Mice,” &c., while many persons call them “Moles,” though they are not in the least related to that family. They are all of small size, with shorter and heavier forms than the true mice; the eyes are small; the ears short and mostly concealed by the fur, which is soft, thick and very generally of a dark color on the upper parts; the head is large; the snout blunt; and the tail short.

The food and general habits of the different species are much alike, though some prefer high, and others wet ground; while others inhabit the woods, prairies, &c. All the species burrow, and none climb trees. The common food of those I have observed is the grasses and other herbaceous plants, their seeds and roots, and the seeds and acorns, as well as the bark of trees, in the woods, with grain and vegetables, when inhabiting cultivated fields. Some are omnivorous as has been observed in their habits while in captivity. To what extent they eat animal food, when at liberty, I am unable to say, though it is probable that they consume some insects in summer; and they may even obtain a few, with the pupae and eggs of more, concealed in the grass, traversed by them in winter. Some kinds, at least, lay up stores of food for winter. All are active at this time, moving about in the coldest weather, and never hibernate like marmots.

One characteristic, certainly possessed by all the species in common, is their ability to destroy the products of the farm. I know of no mammals more injurious to the farmers in Northern Illinois than these seemingly insignificant little meadow-mice. Few, if any, escape their depredations, though the full amount of damage done by them is but little known; and yet they are usually thought even unworthy of consideration. Such of our farmers as cut their corn and leave it standing in shocks for some time in the field, as is usually done here, will find upon examination that in many, if not every one of the shocks, there may be found one or more pair of meadow-mice, which have dug for themselves burrows in the ground beneath, and have often carried thither a store of corn; while in these, or ensconced in the protecting corn-stalks above, they have built themselves a nest, in which they can lead a very comfortable sort of life, regaling themselves, when hungry, upon the corn. Now, a pair of mice will not, it is true, eat enough corn to alarm a farmer for the safety of his crop; but let any one examine a large field of corn, thus cut and left standing on the ground a month or two, where these mice abound, and carefully estimate the average amount of corn destroyed in each shock, observing that which has been buried in the burrow; and then multiply that by the number of shocks inhabited by these pests, and it will be often found that they have really consumed or destroyed a large amount. In meadows, they do much injury by devouring the roots and stems of Timothy, clover, and other plants used for hay. This mischief, however, is seldom noticed by farmers; or, if it is at all, in districts where moles abound, all the blame is laid upon them, as indeed, is very much of the damage done by meadow-mice wherever the two exist together. They also do great mischief by killing young plants in grain-fields; and, soon after the seed is sown, they destroy many of the grains, little stores of which may be found collected in shallow excavations. These are often not eaten, and, germinating, astonish and scandalize the farmer by the appearance of a thick clump of plants where he thought he had sown his seed quite uniformly. They also dig up grain that has just sprouted; and, by examining fields of young wheat, oats, &c., spots will be seen where they have dug down, guided by the growing blades, and taken off the grain. In a nursery, where apple-seeds were planted in autumn, I have observed that, during fall and spring, so many of the seeds were dug up by these mice as to leave long gaps in the rows of seedlings, the empty shells of the seeds being found lying about the rows from which they had been taken. They congregate in stacks of grain and hay, sometimes in exceedingly great numbers, destroying all the lower parts, by cutting galleries through them in every direction.

The greatest mischief done by meadow-mice, is the gnawing of bark from fruit-trees. The complaints are constant and grievous, throughout the Northern States, of the destruction of orchard and nursery trees by the various species of arvicolae. The entire damage done by them in this way may be estimated, perhaps at millions of dollars. If any think this too large an estimate, let them inquire, even in a small neighborhood, where much attention is paid to fruit-growing, and it will be found that, wherever they abound, the injuries committed by these pests are frequently among the most serious difficulties encountered by the pomologist. This is especially the case at the West, where no care is taken to protect the trees against them, careless orchardists allowing grass to grow about the roots of their fruit-trees, and thus kindly furnishing the arvicolae with excellent nesting places, in winter, and rendering the trees doubly liable to be girdled. In the nurseries, in Northern Illinois, I have seen whole rows of young apple-trees stripped of their bark for a foot or two above the ground. Thousands of fruit-trees, as well as evergreens, and other ornamental trees and shrubs, are at times thus killed in a nursery in one winter. The mice are the most mischievous in winters of deep snow. It is usually thought that they only gnaw bark when no other food is to be obtained; but it is more probable that it is palatable to them at all times. Confined specimens, while abundantly supplied with food of all kinds, ate the bark from twigs placed in their cage. One reason why fruit-trees are most girdled in times of deep snow is, that the meadow-mice can then better move about, at a distance from their burrows, being protected by the snow, under which they construct numerous pathways, and are thus enabled to travel comfortably in search of food, always to be obtained in abundance, where there is any kind of perennial grass, or the seeds of annual plants. Aided by the snow, too, they climb up at the sides of the trees to gnaw the bark at a considerable height from the ground. Rabbits are often accused of gnawing bark from trees, when the mischief has really been done by meadow-mice. Many times, in spring, when a florist uncovers some choice plant he has carefully protected during the winter by straw, &c., he is grieved and chagrined to find, instead of a fine dianthus, or half-hardy rose, two nimble, black-eyed arvicolae, which have found good winter-quarters in the shelter provided for the plant, that has furnished them food. Not a little injury do they to vegetables of all kinds, destroying young plants of peas, beans, cabbages, &c., as well as digging up seeds of all sorts, and gnawing potatoes, beets, and other roots. In short, the catalogue of their depredations is endless.

It is related that, some 40 or 50 years ago, a European meadow-mouse (Arvicola agrestis)[1] was so numerous and destructive in parts of England as to cause great damage and serious alarm, ruining whole grain-fields, and threatening to destroy all the young trees in the New Forest and Forest of Dean. In the latter, alone, no less than thirty thousands of these animals were entrapped in three months, while great numbers were killed by birds and beasts of prey. This great increase was, beyond doubt, owing to the destruction of the animals appointed to keep them in check; hence let those of our farmers who, in their ignorance of Nature’s laws, wantonly destroy them, beware, lest the arvicolae also multiply to the same alarming extent in this country.

Meadow-mice are very prolific, bringing forth young several times a year, and usually as many as five or six at a birth. To check this enormous increase, they have numerous natural destroyers. Though mostly nocturnal, they are also active by day; and one of their greatest enemies in this vicinity is the Northern Shrike, or butcher-bird, (Lanius borealis)[2], the food of which consists almost wholly of arvicolae and a few prairie white-footed mice (Mus bairdii)[3] during his sojourn with us, in his spring and fall migrations. This bird takes his stand, day after day, upon the same tree or fence-stake, and from this post surveys the surrounding fields, in which no mouse may now show himself in safety. The result of the shrike’s watchfulness and prowess may be seen, in part in the bodies of the numerous mice, fastened to the branches of bushes or on fences, sometimes partly eaten, sometimes having only the brains taken out, but oftener entire. Considering what he has devoured, besides these, the large numbers destroyed by the shrike may be readily supposed. The Southern shrike (Lanius ludovicianus) which breeds largely in the prairie districts throughout this State, is also an enemy to be dreaded by the meadow-mice. Though feeding more upon insects than its larger cousin, and being perhaps, a less successful mouser, its destruction of arvicolae in summer is well known, and has gained for it the name of “Mouse Bird,” in Central Illinois. This bird not only pounces upon them when they are moving about but finds the nests on the surface, and digs out the inmates with its bill and claws. A domesticated brown sand-hill crane (Grus canadensis) which I kept for several years, spent much time in hunting about the fields for the nests of meadow-mice. He became expert in finding them; and, when they were situated upon or near the surface, he would dig them out with his long and powerful beak, and, after first killing all the inmates, proceed to swallow them whole, with much apparent relish. In spring, I have seen him thus destroy several families of old and young arvicolae in a day. Cranes are omnivorous, and large feeders, and if all are as good mouse-catchers as my pet, they must destroy great quantities on the prairie. The owls, also, devour them to some extent, in timber, especially; while the short-eared owl, (Brachyotus cassinii[4], of Brewer,) which is strictly a prairie bird here, feeds largely upon them. This owl is diurnal, and may be seen flying low over the surface, in search of meadow-mice, in broad day, both in winter and summer. The hawks all prey upon them, too, from the little sparrow-hawk to the great red-tailed buzzard. The marsh-hawk lives mostly upon them in this region, and is observed sweeping along close to the ground hunting for them in every field. Dr. Hoy informs me that, near Racine, he observed, in autumn, a flock of black-hawks (Archibuteo sancti-joannis)[5] twenty or thirty in number, to frequent a high knoll to which numerous meadow-mice had been driven by the inundation of the surrounding low-lands. This they visited morning and evening for over a month, during which time they appeared to feed upon nothing else than meadow-mice. One of them, shot late in autumn, was exceedingly fat, and had the remains of four full-grown arvicolae in his stomach. Dr. Hoy estimated the number destroyed by the flock in six weeks, at over eight thousand. He says that they form the chief food of this hawk in the West, and that it should be regarded as a friend to the farmer, the more so as it does not make predatory descents upon the farm-yard. Arvicolae are the legitimate food for the prairie rattlesnake, or massasauga (Crotalophorus tergeminus)[6]. In many specimens of this snake examined, I have not found one, the stomach of which did not contain the remains of meadow-mice. The rattlesnake can readily enter their burrows, and is certainly more or less nocturnal; so that the arvicolae, when out at night, fall an easy prey to this voracious reptile, which, though noted for its ability to endure wonderful fasts, even of a year or more, in captivity, is, nevertheless, a huge feeder naturally. I have taken the partly-digested bodies of five adult arvicolae, with the remains of two small garter-snakes, and some birds’ feathers, from the stomach of a rattlesnake; and have repeatedly found the remains of several mice, in various stages of digestion, in the stomach of one of them, showing that they had been caught at different times. And, I would here remark, that I have little faith in the opinion popular among farmers that rattlesnakes eat only at long intervals from choice. Observations indicates the contrary. Meadow-mice are also devoured by the common large-striped, or garter-snake, (Eutœnia sirtalis)[7], and are undoubtedly eaten by another garter-snake, (Eutœnia radix)[8], and of the large fox-snake (Scotophis vulpinus)[9]. All the larger snakes probably prey upon them in other localities. The most abundant species of arvicolae, in this region, are inhabitants of the prairie, and have less to fear from the small timber-loving carnivorous mammals, than those living in the woods. Minks, skunks, and weasels, however, when inhabiting the prairie, devour many; foxes, also, eat them, and prairie wolves[10] dig open their burrows and feed largely upon them. Badgers, no doubt, also destroy many. As stated, in noticing the striped spermophile, that animal makes many a meal upon them, as well, perhaps, as Franklin’s spermophile. Domestic cats hunt them eagerly, eating them in preference to house-mice. It is to be observed that the flesh of the arvicolae is sweet and delicate, without the disagreeable flavor of the house mice, being, in fact, quite palatable. Judging from the astonishingly savage and carnivorous propensities exhibited by some specimens, in confinement, it is highly probable that, where abundant, they may frequently devour each other. After the annual fires have burned the grass on the prairies, numerous nests of the arvicolae may be found on the ground, the inmates of which, unable to escape, have often been killed, furnishing a feast to the many hawks, owls, &c., which flock to those grand barbecues.

In spite of all this destruction, arvicolae are abundant on the wild prairie. With their exceeding fecundity, how much greater must be their increase in cultivated land, where most of their natural enemies are destroyed. Our farmers kill the small birds of prey with a zeal that would be highly commendable if exhibited in a better cause, while the man is rarely found who does not kill the harmless mouse and insect-eating snakes, with as much eagerness as he would destroy the really objectionable rattlesnake, which is the only [Sic] poisonous[11] reptile on the prairies of Illinois and other Western States.

Let one of our prairie farmers, who regard these pests as “inoffensive little mice that only steal a few kernels of corn,” investigate their habits carefully for a year, and he will be very apt to conclude that meadow-mice are a kind of farm stock that are “hardy and excellent breeders,” but rather expensive “to keep.” It may be, he will think it best to forbid killing, too, on his farm, the prairie hawks, owls, and shrikes, as well as harmless snakes. This he will be still more apt to do, if he has observed, as I have, that, besides mice, the food of these is chiefly insects. I would ask any observing farmer if the ungrateful and foolish destruction of those friends of agriculture is not a disgrace to a community calling itself civilized and enlightened?

The protection of such of their natural enemies as are not themselves too mischievous should, be the first care of farmers injured by arvicolae. Any dog, which can be taught to hunt them, will scratch and destroy great numbers. I have observed dogs which were encouraged, to spend most of their time, day after day, in hunting their burrows, and thus quite ridding fields of them for the time. On farms, where there is no grain left out in autumn, they will collect under little bunches of hay placed for the purpose, especially if baited with an ear or two of damaged corn; and, by examining these occasionally, with the assistance of a dog, many may be killed. Any farmer with young sons who exhibit a predilection for the “chase,” should furnish them with a lot of common mouse-traps to be bought at the cost of a few cents apiece; and, thus equipped, the juvenile “sportsman” will often “bag” large quantities of this “game,” and be doing far better, withal, than some of their older brothers, who, perhaps, are wasting more costly ammunition, meanwhile, in shooting useful birds.

To wage war effectually against these, or any other of the animals the depredations of which should be resisted, farmers must work together, all in a neighborhood, taking measures for one to destroy the injurious insects or mammals, and protect the reptiles, birds, and carnivorous quadrupeds, which are the enemies of the depredators on a small farm, if his neighbors on every side pursue an opposite course.

A little care will frequently prevent much of the destruction caused by arvicolae. Farmers inform me that, by putting into long, rather than short shocks, the corn to be left out, it escapes much injury, these animals apparently foreseeing that it would not, in this form, afford them sufficient protection in winter. In preparing half-hardy plants for winter, in gardens infested with arvicolae, straw should not be used. Inverted sods, placed over tender roses, &c., pegged flat to the ground, do not furnish the meadow-mice a resting place; and, as it is not the extreme cold that kills plants in winter, but rather the exposure to wet, and sudden changes in temperature, this method is often better, under any circumstances, than covering them with straw. Arvicolae are always most injurious on farms grown up with weeds, which furnish them resting places and food, at times when they could not otherwise remain, as it is to be observed that they do not burrow on bare ground. Hence, small patches of grass, in large and well-cultivated fields, will always be found full of their burrows, in regions where they prevail. The greatest injury committed by them is the girdling of fruit-trees; and here their ravages may often be prevented merely by clearing away all grass and weeds from about the roots. But it must be remembered, that they will travel under the snow, on clear ground, to some distance from their burrows; and, therefore, if possible, no uncultivated spots should be allowed within several rods of the trees, on farms much infested by them. I have observed hundreds of apple-trees girdled, in a nursery kept free of weeds, but situated within three or four rods of unbroken prairie inhabited by these pests.

Wrapping the trunks of fruit-trees with strips of muslin, so arranged as to shed rain, may at times be advisable; the same cloth being applied every fall, and removed in spring, will last several years. It is said that neither mice nor rabbits will gnaw through it when thus applied; but dipping it in tar no doubt would be beneficial.

[1] Currently referred to by the binomial name Microtus agrestis [Linnaeus, 1761].

[2] Currently referred to by the binomial name Lanius excubitor [Linnaeus, 1758].

[3] Currently referred to by the binomial name Peromyscus maniculatus [Wagner, 1845].

[4] I suspect the author is referring to Asio flammeus [Pontoppidan, 1763].

[5] Currently referred to by the binomial name Buteo lagopus [Pontoppidan, 1763].

[6] Currently referred to by the binomial name Sistrus catenatus [Rafinesque, 1818].

[7] Currently referred to by the binomial name Thamnophis sirtalis [Linnaeus, 1758].

[8] Currently referred to by the binomial name Thamnophis radix [Baird and Girard, 1853].

[9] Currently referred to by the binomial name Pantherophis vulpinus [Baird and Girard, 1853].

[10] The ‘Prairie Wolf’ is the Coyote (Canis latrans) [Say, 1823].

[11] The correct term here is venomous.

Migratory, or Common Gray- and Black-Squirrel

pages 62b–65

[Plate VI.a, Photo 4]

Sciurus migratorius [Audubon and Bachman, 1851]

Description.—The adult male measures about 12 inches from the nose to the root of the tail; vertebrae of the tail, 10½ inches. In color, there are two very different varieties of this species commonly met with. One is of a blackish-brown on the upper parts, lighter beneath and with some rusty markings on the feet and face. The other is of a gray color, with reddish-yellow markings about the head, belly, sides, and feet. These two varieties are commonly considered among our farmers, as distinct species, and are respectively called the “gray” and “black” squirrel; but any one living in the woods may, by a little observation, satisfy himself of their identity as one species, and the females will be found to bring forth specimens of both varieties at one birth, and the two live and breed together without regard to color. They are now known under the two very different names of the “black” and the “gray” squirrel; but while there are other black and gray-squirrels, would it not be better for our farmers to adopt the highly appropriate name of the “migratory squirrel” for this species—the more so as Audubon and Bachman have, with good taste, given this as its specific name?

The gray squirrel is the most abundant, and, it is said, sometimes exists in great numbers where none of the black ones are found. The black variety, however, is sometimes, though rarely, the most numerous in certain localities. In a lot of near fifty, shot near the Rock River in Illinois, there was not a single gray one, all being of the black variety.

In the northern states, the migratory squirrel replaces the Sciurus carolinensis, of the South. It exists throughout the Eastern, Middle and in some of the western states, and is said by Audubon and Bachman to be found as far north as Hudson’s Bay. In Illinois, it exists only in the northern part of the state, being replaced by the Carolina gray-squirrel in the South. It exists abundantly in Northern Illinois, Southern Wisconsin, and Central Iowa, but to the northward, I am informed by Dr. Spear B. Davis, of Shakepee, Scott county, Minnesota, that it is not observed in the southeastern portion of that Territory. I learn from Dr. Hoy that it does not exist in Northern Wisconsin. Audubon and Bachman, however, mention its being found on the Upper Missouri.

This is the most abundant of our American squirrels. It has a wide geographical range, and is prolific, and in many localities exists in almost incredible abundance. The immense numbers, heretofore mentioned as killed in one year for the bounty offered by Pennsylvania, were chiefly of this species. In Northern Ohio, I have seen them in such numbers as to to be truly astonishing. Dr. Hoy relates that he knew a hunter in that state to kill one hundred and sixty in a day, and that, too, when they were not unusually abundant in the locality. In parts of Michigan, Illinois, Southern Wisconsin, and Indiana, they are no less numerous. Existing in such myriads, their depredations, of course, become at times a source of serious damage to the farmer. Fields of corn, and occasionally wheat, are much injured or entirely destroyed by them. I am informed that persons have sometimes kept watch in their fields to drive them off, and thus prevent the destruction of the whole crop. This species appears to increase in numbers, in certain districts, for a time after their settlement.

The migratory squirrel is at home both in low, heavy timber, and higher and somewhat more open woods, though it loves the heavily-timbered, elevated ground best. It never frequents the outskirts of the woods, of which the fox-squirrel is so fond, and does not affect oak openings, nor the prairie groves, unless well timbered. This is one of the most active of our squirrels, and, when out in fine weather, and not engaged in feeding, may be seen scampering about the trees, as if much exercise were necessary to its existence. It leaves the trees unwillingly, and in its progress, travels as much as possible upon fallen logs in the woods, and on fences in the fields. It does not run readily upon the ground, and, when pursued, if possible, soon takes to a tree.

The most interesting feature in the habits of this animal is the remarkable migration performed at times by large bodies of them. I am not aware that any of these extensive migrations have been observed in Northern Illinois, but in the neighboring states of Wisconsin and Michigan, and in other localities where the species abounds, they not uncommonly occur. Immense numbers congregate in autumn, and move off together, continuing their progress in the same general direction, whatever it may be, not even turning aside for large streams. Ordinarily averse to to entering the water, they now take to it boldly, and, though swimming with difficulty, manage to cross broad rivers, like the Niagara and the Ohio, though many are drowned in the attempt. The vulgar notion that squirrels, in crossing water, “are ferried over on bits of wood and bark, using their tails for sails,” is, it is, perhaps, needless to say, entirely fabulous. Sometimes, when on these migrations, especially after crossing rivers, the squirrels become so fatigued as to be easily captured, and thousands are then killed by boys armed merely with sticks and stones. I learn from Dr. John A. Kennicott that, during one of these migrations, innumerable squirrels swam across the river Niagara, and landed near Buffalo, New York, in such a state of exhaustion that the boys caught them in their hands, or knocked them from fences and bushes with poles. It must not be supposed, however that the squirrels, in these migrations, rush ahead without stopping, or turning to the right or left for food. Better would it be for some unhappy farmers if such were the case, for ill fare the corn fields which they visit. Generally, they are observed to make their appearance in unusual abundance, running along the fences, and up every tree; and, though they may often go out of their way to follow a fence, or to enter the woods, in preference to crossing open ground, or even to stay some time in one locality, they are always tending forward more or less rapidly in one direction.

The reason for these migrations is not satisfactorily explained. That they are caused by want of food is hardly probable, as the squirrels are found to be fat at the time, and as often leave localities abounding with food as otherwise. After one of these grand migrations, very few of the species are found in the localities from which they have moved, and these, as if alarmed at the unusual solitude, are silent and shy. They rapidly increase in numbers, however, and, in a few years, are as abundant as before. I am not aware that they ever migrate except when exceedingly abundant. Of these immense hordes, but few probably survive. No sudden increase in their numbers was heard of in Southern Wisconsin after the several migrations from Northern Illinois. Many are drowned in attempting to cross streams as has been stated; not a few are destroyed by man; some die from utter exhaustion; and, when thus forced to travel, in an unnatural manner, upon the ground, they fall an easy prey to rapacious birds and mammals, all of which feast when the squirrels migrate. I learn from Dr. Hoy, that one of these migrations is said to have taken place in Southern Wisconsin in 1842; he witnessed another in 1847, and a third in 1852. From these facts, and, from observations made in Ohio and elsewhere, he is of the opinion that the migrations, in most cases, at least, occur at intervals of five years; and, if he be right, the squirrels, which are now exceedingly abundant again in Southern Wisconsin, may be expected to migrate in the autumn of 1857. He further says, that the migrations observed by him, in Southern Wisconsin, occurred when the mast was exceedingly abundant and the squirrels in excellent condition. Near Racine, they were observed passing southward in very large numbers for about two weeks, at the end of September and the beginning of October; and it was a month before all had passed. They moved along rather leisurely, stopping to feed in the fields, and upon the abundant nuts and acorns of the forests. So far had they departed from their accustomed habits that they were seen on the prairie, four or five miles from any timber; but even there, as usual, they disliked to travel on the ground, and ran along the fences wherever it was possible.

The food of these squirrels is similar to that of the fox-squirrel. They are also very fond of the berries of the black-haw (Viburnum lentago). They are more prolific than the other species, from four to six young being produced at a birth; two and perhaps three litters are brought forth each year, the first quite early, generally in March. The gravid female is very shy and silent, keeping close in the hole, and venturing out for food with caution.

The migratory squirrel is somewhat social; several will feed together, and five or six occasionally inhabit one hole in winter. Where not much hunted, it is noisy and bold. Frequently, when a dog barks or a gun is discharged in the woods where they abound, dozens of them will commence barking in every direction. They do not love the neighborhood of man, and though they much affect the fruits of the farmer’s labor in the corn field, when they can steal it without coming too near the house, they will not take up their residence near his dwellings.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

In Mammalian Species № 480 (published by the American Society of Mammalogists in 1994), the binomial name Sciurus migratorius [Audubon and Bachman, 1851] is listed as a junior synonym of Sciurus carolinensis [Gmelin, 1788].

Based upon where Illinois, Pennsylvania, and Buffallo fall within the range map provided in that same article, the squirrels in those locations referenced by the author using the binomial name Sciurus migratorius is the subspecies currently known by the trinomial name Sciurus carolinensis pennsylvanicus [Ord in Guthrie, 1815] and the squirrels in Wisconsin referenced by the author using the binomial name Sciurus migratorius is the subspecies currently known by the trinomial name Sciurus carolinensis hypophaeus [Merriam, 1886].

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Eastern Gray Squirrel’. Although multiple subspecies are recognized, common names at the subspecies level do not appear to be used in most current literature.

For more information on the Eastern Gray Squirrel, see:

Mammalian Species № 480: DOI:10.2307/3504224
ITIS Report for TSN 930435 (S. c. pennsylvanicus)
ITIS Report for TSN 930434 (S. c. hypophaeus)

True Rats and Mice

pages 108b–110

The species of the old genus Mus are numerous, and all very prolific. Three have been introduced, throughout the civilized world, by commerce. Departing entirely from what must have been their original mode of life, these have taken up their residence permanently in the dwellings of man, rendering themselves highly obnoxious by their mischievous habits.

Common House-Mouse

Mus musculus [Linnaeus, 1758]

This is not a native species, but has been introduced from Europe. Whence it first came is not known. It always follows civilized man. Its habits and depredations in the house are too well known to need comment. In Illinois, I have found it breeding and living throughout the year in the fields, in considerable numbers. It digs burrows, sometimes in the open ground, at others under corn shocks, or other shelter, and there collects its store of food, thus assuming the habits of the field mouse, when adopting its home in the fields.

Brown-Rat

Mus decumanus [Pallas, 1779]

This exceedingly troublesome animal is said to have been a native of Persia. It is only within the present century that it has been introduced into this country or Europe. It has spread with such rapidity that it is now abundant throughout all the long-settled portions of the Union, though it is only within a few years that it has been known in our recently-settled and interior prairie regions; and in some parts of which, indeed, it has not yet made its appearance at all. It often lives in the fields, like the preceding, and excavates large burrows under corn shocks, &c., into one of which a pair will sometimes carry a full half bushel of shelled corn. In its burrow, it makes a large nest of the soft corn husks and silks, or of grass.

Farmers are occasionally surprised by the sudden and entire disappearance of the brown-rats from their houses, where they were abundant a short time before; but, upon making inquiry in such cases, they may also find that some of their neighbors are quite as much surprised, and considerably more annoyed, at the equally sudden appearance of large numbers on their premises; and these migrations are by no means unfrequent.

For figure of the wood-rat (Neotoma floridana)[1] of the southern states, see Plate XIV.b.

Black-Rat

[Photo 23]

Mus rattus [Linnaeus, 1758]

This species, which seems to have been introduced originally from Asia, has been known in Europe and America much longer than the brown-rat, before which it always disappears. The black-rat was once abundant in parts of the United States, but is now unknown in many localities where it formerly bred. I believe it has rarely been found in a few localities in this region, the brown-rat having apparently found its way here before it.

Like the two preceding species, this is omnivorous, feeding upon almost any kind of vegetable or flesh. Both rats devour eggs, and even capture living animals, with all the ferocity of strictly carnivorous species.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The binomial nomenclature Mus musculus [Linnaeus, 1758] used by the author is still valid.

In 1803, Fisher described the genus Rattus to distinguish old-world rats from old-world mice.

The binomial nomenclature Mus decumanus [Pallas, 1779] has been invalidated as a junior synonym of Rattus norvegicus [Berkenhout, 1769].

The binomial nomenclature Mus rattus [Linnaeus, 1758] is invalid, with the species having been moved into the genus Rattus. It is thus currently known as Rattus rattus [Linnaeus, 1758].

[1] I am a bit puzzled as to why this plate was included in the original article.

Muskrat

pages 105b–108

[Plate XIV.a, Photo 20]

Fiber zibethicus [Linnaeus, 1766]

Description.—A full-grown muskrat is about 15 inches in length, from nose to root of tail, and the tail is 10 inches. The body is heavy, eyes small, ears concealed, and incisor teeth large; the tail large, nearly naked, and flattened laterally; legs, short, hind-feet, with the toes flattened and partly palmated; beneath the long hair is a coat of dense, soft and very warm fur; color of the body, ashy-brown above, ashy on the underparts.

The muskrat, or “Musquash,” abounds in the greater part of North America, though not in certain of the southeastern states. It is found northward to the Polar Sea. It is strictly aquatic, its stout tail and muscular hind-legs, being provided with broad feet and toes, furnish it efficient means of locomotion in the water, while its thick, downy fur protects it from the wet. On land, its movements are as awkward as those of a duck. It naturally seeks its food in the water, away from which it never takes up its abode.

Though frequently seen abroad by day, muskrats are nocturnal, moving mostly by night. They are to some extent gregarious, a number uniting to make houses and burrows. In most localities, where the situation admits of it, they construct houses in the water with much skill; in marshes and ponds, or along sluggish streams, when protected from the current, they form large piles of sticks, leaves, rushes, carices, and various aquatic plants, the whole well stuck together with mud, and having a comfortable chamber in the center, entered only through a hole from below the surface of the water. This is the winter home of muskrats, more than one pair usually occupying the same nest. Near by, in the bank, is generally a burrow, with numerous and extensive galleries, in which they take refuge when driven from their houses in winter, and in which the young are commonly produced. These burrows, like the houses, always have the entrance under water.

The muskrat is active in winter, seeking his food under the ice, and carrying it into its burrow or house to be eaten. Though roots are sometimes found in a nest in winter, they are only such as have been recently brought in, no considerable stores of food being collected. The food, in winter, appears to consist of roots of aquatic plants. In summer, it also feeds upon the leaves of various plants, as well as upon muscles, (Unio anodonta and U. plicatus, etc.,)[1] of which they consume great quantities in some of our rivers. Collecting them from the bottom, it carries them in its teeth to a log or stone, where, sitting upon its haunches, and grasping them in the fore-paws, it opens the shells with the incisors as skillfully as it could be done with an oyster-knife. In this way, large piles of shells are collected around stones and logs, by examining which the conchologist may often find rare species, brought from the mud by these animals which have been more successful collectors than himself. I have observed that those species with thin shells are most sought for, and have often found large specimens of Unio plicatus unopened among the piles of empty shells, the muskrat apparently considering them not worth the trouble of gnawing apart the valves at the back, in which manner the heavy shells are sometimes opened.

Muskrats are seldom seriously injurious to the farmer’s crops, though they are occasionally mischievous in fields adjoining water inhabited by them. I have observed ears of corn dragged to their nests, and they sometimes make great havoc in vegetable gardens where they show an especial fondness for parsnips and muskmelons. Their greatest injury, however, is committed by burrowing in embankments formed to confine water, milldams being often much damaged in this way. They also frequently destroy artificial ponds for collecting ice. Except in eating mollusks, and occasionally a dead fish, I am not aware that this species departs from a vegetable diet.

This species is pugnacious, and resists courageously when attacked. The males sometimes have fierce battles, and trappers state that the tail is occasionally mutilated, or cut entirely off in these combats. The voice is a sharp squeak, and some hunters will call the males within shooting distance by imitating it. From five to seven young—more or less—are produced in April or May. In this region, at least, the muskrat’s worst enemy is the mink, which, swimming and diving readily, not only enters their burrows and houses, but pursues them in the water. The mink does not find an easy prey, as the muskrats fight savagely; but, emboldened by hunger, he finally kills his victim, when he does not scruple to devour the whole body. Otters probably kill them, also, as they are occasionally found in muskrat houses.

Upon land, the muskrats are easily captured by various mammals and rapacious birds. They are readily trapped, as they are not at all suspicious, which operation, in former times, furnished many a youth with pocket-money, while older hunters made it their chief occupation. A steel-trap, baited with pieces of parsnip, or of sweet apple is generally used; or sometimes a trap without bait is placed in their runways. In winter, they are caught by driving a long-pronged spear through the tops of their houses into their nest, where they are lying together, several being frequently transfixed at a blow from a spear provided with several prongs. The indigenous peoples killed them thus, even with their traditional stone-headed spears. Sometimes they are shot, when sitting on the ice on sunny days in winter, or while swimming about, or basking on logs, in spring. In our Western rivers and lakelets, they are occasionally shot by hunters, who paddle silently about in canoes on moonlight nights.

Muskrat skins have been a considerable item in the commerce of America. Formerly, when the fur was largely used for napping “beaver hats,” so called, they were of greater value than at present, being then worth more than the skin of mink, selling, indeed, for from 40 to 50 cents[2] each. Changes in the fashions of late years, including the general introduction of silk hats, have resulted happily for the persecuted muskrats, and for the last ten or twenty years their skins have sold from 8 to 15 cents[3] cents each, and even as low as 6¼ cents; and trapping them has in a measure ceased. Within the last year or two, however, they have sold for somewhat better prices, being now largely used for making caps, gloves, and some articles of ladies’ furs.

In Northern Illinois, the muskrat has not been so long persecuted by man, and therefore has not learned to fear his presence so much as in longer-settled regions. It is accordingly oftener seen out by day here than in the older states, where, in some localities, it is said to be almost strictly nocturnal, and exceedingly shy withal. Here they may not only be found feeding by day, but even at work, building their houses; and, while hunting ducks along the Des Plaines River, I have frequently shot them in broad day, as they sat upon logs at the water’s edge.

In place of the living brooks and creeks, which drain wooded and uneven lands, we have here, on our level prairies, numerous broad and shallow depressions, that carry off the surplus water in rainy times, becoming dry in summer, except in places where they are deeper and form large basins in which the body of water is so great as to hold out, despite the evaporation in ordinary seasons, while some are constantly supplied by springs, and never become dry. In these prairie water-courses and ponds, or sloughs[♦], as they are called, the muskrats were very abundant twenty years ago; but, though still occasionally seen in the larger ones, and numerous in some, their numbers are very small compared with their former abundance. In the sloughs, their houses were built like those in wooded rivers or marshes. They usually had burrows in the dry land at the edge of the sloughs, and when there was no spot nearer, sufficiently elevated to be above high water, a burrow would be dug at some distance—sometimes 15 or 20 rods—from the edge of the slough, and approached by a gallery excavated the entire distance under the sod. Some, in very wide marshes, appeared to have no burrows, living always in their large nests. Though the young are generally brought forth in burrows, they were often found in the houses in the sloughs, only one female, however, remaining in a house. The sloughs inhabited by them being of no great depth, and often dried up in summer, or frozen to the bottom in winter, the muskrats were frequently found wandering about in search of water; and even lately I have, in dry summers, occasionally found them on the prairie at great distances from water. Since the prairies have been settled and cultivated, the muskrats are generally observed living permanently only in large marshes, lakelets, and streams; they seem quite as much at home, however, in these, when situated on the prairie, as when in the timber; and old trappers assure me that they have never seen “rat” more abundant than they have been on the prairies of Northern Illinois.

The Potawatomi Tribe call the muskrat zheshko; they eat the flesh, when boiled with corn or roasted, or cooked in various ways. The hunters and trappers consider the hind-quarters very palatable, when roasted on coals; and they, as well as the Potawatomi, esteem the tail a great delicacy.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

This species was originally described as Castor zibethicus [Linnaeus, 1766]. The genus Fiber [Dumeril, 1805; TSN 900101] used by the author is now considered to be a homonyn and junior synonym of Castor. However, the species is now the type species for the monotypic genus Ondatra [Link, 1795; TSN 180317] resulting in the binomial name Ondatra zibethicus [Linnaeus, 1766] as the currently used binomial nomenclature. Numerous subspecies have been described but many do not currently accept them as valid.

For more information on the Muskrat, see:

Mammalian Species № 141: DOI:10.2307/3504016
ITIS Report for TSN 180318

[♦] This is pronounced sloos, in our Western vernacular, and slows, by Walker and Webster. They are called “sloughs,” as well when slight depressions, containing water only after rain, or when large marshes. Thus, a slough, on high prairie, may have a solid, grassy bottom, or it may be miry and filled with bulrushes and other strictly aquatic plants, the name not being restricted to muddy and miry places, as the word “slough” would indicate in its original sense. The Potawatomi Tribe called a slough wabskoki, a wet prairie; a very large one they called chi wabskoki, big wet prairie; and an extensive, marshy water-course, which forms the chief source of the north branch of the Chicago River, is here very generally known as the “Sko-kee.” The prairie sloughs are the favorite homes of many animals and plants, some of which seem peculiar to them.

[1] These binomial names do not appear to be valid, and I am not certain which muscle species the author was referencing.

[2] Roughly $12.00 to $15.00 in 2020 money.

[3] Roughly $2.50 to $4.50 in 2020 money.

Needed Photographs

This is a list of quality high resolution photographs needed to complete this project. Any help would be appreciated.

The photographs must have a license that is compatible with the Creative Commons BY-SA 4.0 license use for this digital publication.

I can be contacted at pipfroschpress@gmail.com

Eastern Fox Squirrel
Melanistic Western Fox Squirrel
Red Squirrel
Southern Flying Squirrel
White-footed Mouse
Deer Mouse
Meadow Jumping Mouse
Prairie Vole
Woodland Vole
House Mouse
Brown Rat
Black Rat

Eastern Fox Squirrel

Specifically needed is a photograph of Sciurus niger vulpinus.

Photographs I have found online claiming to be this subspecies that could potentially used either have a stated locale outside the range of this subspecies, or do not state a locale and look suspiciously like Sciurus niger rufiventer.

This squirrel use to be present in the southen part of Pennsylvania but apparently is either exceedingly rare there now, or has been extirpated.

It is reportedly still present within six counties of North Carolina at the northern end of the Blue Mountain range, and also in Virgina west of the Blue Mountains.

My preference would be from North Carolina part of the range in a state park away from heavy urban areas, as Sciurus niger rufiventer is often introduced in urban areas. There are several state parks there, I am guessing one of them has a healthy population.

See Fox Squirrel—North Carolina Wildlife Profiles (PDF) for a range map.

Note that two subspecies of Sciurus niger are in North Carolina. S. n. vulpinus is the smaller range shown on the map, where North Carolina hits Tennessee and Virginia.

Melanistic Western Fox Squirrel

I need a photograph of a Melanistic (black) squirrel that is unquestionably a Western Fox Squirrel (Sciurus niger rufiventer) and not a Gray Squirrel (Sciurus carolinensis).

Preferably this would be within the range of Sciurus niger rufiventer but outside the range of Sciurus carolinensis.

This photograph would replace Photo 5 which is not positively identified at the species level and which I suspect is actually Sciurus carolinensis.

Red Squirrel

I need a photograph of Tamiasciurus hudsonicus from Illinois or Wisconsin.

The photograph I have is beautiful but it is from Alaska, which is not exactly the western Great Lakes region.

This photograph would replace Photo 7.

Southern Flying Squirrel

Preferably from Illinois or Wisconsin, I need to have a quality photograph of Glaucomys volans.

Given the highly nocturnal nature of this species and the desire for the gliding membrane to be exposed, a posed taxidermy specimen may be what is required, but please do not kill one for that purpose. Hopefully a natural history museum that allows photographs has one.

White-footed Mouse

Preferably from Illinois or Wisconsin, I need a quality photograph of Peromyscus leucopus.

Deer Mouse

From within Illinois or Wisconsin, I need a quality photograph of Peromyscus maniculatus.

The existing photograph is from Arizona and it is quite possible a future taxonomy review will reveal it to be a different species than what is in Illinois.

Even if that never happens, the species can be quite variable and I would prefer to have a photograph representative of the western Great Lakes region.

This photograph would replace Photo 15.

Meadow Jumping Mouse

Preferably from Illinois or Wisconsin, I need a quality photograph of Zapus hudsonius.

Prairie Vole

Preferably from Illinois or Wisconsin, I need a quality photograph of Microtus ochrogaster.

Woodland Vole

Preferably from Illinois or Wisconsin, I need a quality photograph of Microtus pinetorum.

House Mouse

Locality does not matter but it should be alive, wild (opposed to domestic pet variety), and in a natural setting. I need a quality photograph of Mus musculus.

Brown Rat

Locality does not matter but it should be alive, wild (opposed to domestic pet variety), and in a natural setting. I need a quality photograph of Rattus norvegicus.

The photograph must include the full tail length as that is an easy identification key when distinguishing this species from Rattus rattus.

Black Rat

Locality does not matter but it should be alive, wild (opposed to domestic pet variety), and in a natural setting. I need a quality photograph of Rattus rattus. The existing photograph is of a posed taxidermied specimen.

The photograph must include the full tail length as that is an easy identification key when distinguishing this species from Rattus norvegicus.

This photograph would replace Photo 23.

Prairie-Dog

[Plate IX.b]

Spermophilus ludovicianus [Ord, 1815]

Description.—Length of adult male from nose to root of tail, 13 inches; tail, (vertebræ,) 2⅝ inches. Back, reddish-brown mixed with grey and black; belly, soiled white; tail, banded with brown near the tip.

The famous “Prairie Dog,” or “Prairie Squirrel,” exists in great abundance on the plains west of the Missouri River, being also found over a large extent of country at the southward, and it has also been observed as far west as California. At the southward, Captain Marcy found it above Cross Timbers, on the Red River of Louisiana. Though not properly included among the mammals of this region, this squirrel has more resemblance to our grey spermophile in color, and to the wood-chuck (Arctomys monax) in form, than to any other known to our farmers. Its habits are not unlike those of our grey and striped spermophiles. Like them, it is strictly a prairie animal, subsisting upon plants, and probably on some insects.

The prairie dogs are fond of each other’s company, and live together, in great congregations, their numerous burrows, situated close together, being called “prairie-dog towns.” The burrow is much deeper and more extensive than that of either of our two Illinois prairie-squirrels. Like these, it is fond of standing erect near its hole, ventures from it with caution, and hastens into it when alarmed; but, as if it were inquisitive, soon puts out its head again to look at the cause of its fright. Like the rest of the genus, it hibernates. Its note is said to have gained it the name of “Prairie Dog,” but its voice can scarcely bear much resemblance to the bark of a dog, and is probably more like the whistling chatter of our grey and striped spermophiles, though perhaps less musical and clear.

Numbers of our common [Sic] prairie rattlesnakes (Crotalophorus tergeminus)[1], as well as of a small owl, live habitually in the burrows of the prairie-dog. These can hardly be welcome guests of the rightful inhabitants. Though the owl probably feeds chiefly upon insects, it might devour the young; and the rattlesnake certainly does, as well as makes many a meal of the adults.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The binomial nomenclature of this species is an excellent example of the rules of taxonomy nomenclature in action.

The first description of this species that gave it a binomial name came in 1815 by Ord, giving it the name Arctomys ludovicianus placing it in the existing genus Arctomys [Schreber, 1780; TSN 930222].

A second description of this species giving it a binomial name came in 1817 by Rafinesque—apparently unaware Ord had already described it—giving it the name Cynomys socialis. Rafinesque did not believe this species fit any existing genera, so he defined the genus Cynomys using Cynomys socialis as the type species for the genus.

As the Cynomys socialis of Rafinesque is the same species as Arctomys ludovicianus of Ord, Cynomys socialis is an invalid junior synonym because Arctomys ludovicianus was described first.

Kennicott, the author of this paper (1857), recognized that this species did not belong in the genus Arctomys. He placed it in the Ground Squirrel genus Spermophilus [F. Cuvier, 1825; TSN 180145]. I do not know if Kennicott was the first to use Spermophilus ludovicianus or if he followed another naturalist, that binomial combination does not seem to have been used very often.

Just a year later in 1857, in 1858, Baird also recognized that this species did not belong in Arctomys. Baird however did not feel this species belonged in Spermophilus either, or any other genera currently in use. As Rafinesque was the first to recognize this species belonged in a novel genus, even though the binomial name Cynomys socialis is an invalid junior synonym to Arctomys ludovicianus, the rules of taxonomy nomenclature give priority to Cynomys for the genus name since Rafinesque was the first to recognize that this species needed a novel genus. Baird thus correctly used the name Cynomys ludovicianus, combining the specific name from the original description by Ord with the genus name by Rafinesque.

As Cynomys ludovicianus is now the binomial nomenclature for the type species to the genus Cynomys, it is highly unlikely the accepted binomial nomenclature for this species will ever change again. The only ways that could happen:

Cynomys ludovicianus is shown to be a junior synonym for an earlier described species. Not going to happen, this species is clearly distinct from all earlier described species.
Cladistics show that Cynomys ludovicianus aligns closely with a previously described genus such that placing this species in the previously described genus would solve a paraphyletic clade issue. Also highly unlikely to ever happen.

Unless for some reason we are compelled to abandom binomial nomenclature, the species described by Ord will almost certainly always be known as Cynomys ludovicianus [Ord, 1815].

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Black-tailed Prairie Dog’.

For more information on the Black-tailed Prairie Dog, see:

Mammalian Species № 535: DOI:10.2307/3504202
ITIS Report for TSN 180186

[1] The author is almost certainly referring to the Massasauga (Sistrus catenatus) [Rafinesque, 1818]. There is a subspecies with the trinomial name S. c. tergeminus [Say, 1823] and while that subspecies is not present in Illinois, the Massasauga species is present in Illinois and is sometime colloquially called the Prairie Rattlesnake.

The actual Prairie Rattlesnake (Crotalus viridis) [Rafinesque, 1818] is not currently or historically known to be present in Illinois.

Prairie Meadow-Mouse

[Plate XII.a]

Arvicola austerus [Le Conte, 1853]

Description.—Length of head and body of old male in November, 4½ inches from nose to root of tail; tail, (vertebrae,) 1¼ inches; hind-foot thirteen-sixteenths of an inch, from heel to tip of longest toe. On the back, the hairs are deep blue-black at the base, then ringed with cinnamon-brown, and tipped with blackish, a few long hairs, entirely black, interspersed; on the head and along the back, the color is darker. Low on the sides and cheeks the hairs are all tipped with cinnamon-brown, without rings, as they are on the belly also, where they are shorter and thinner, and of a bluish-gray color at the base, thus leaving the belly bluish-gray, tinted with cinnamon. Tail and feet, thinly clothed with short hairs; tail, brownish-gray beneath, blackish above; feet, grayish; whiskers, shorter than the head, some entirely black, others white, with black roots; incisors, clear light lemon-color. The old male in spring, differs from the above, in having less black along the head and back, with very little cinnamon on the belly, while around the root of the tail there is a spot of dark-cinnamon. In this species the belly is usually more or less colored with cinnamon. Summer specimens from Wisconsin have the hair on the belly all tipped with light rusty-yellow. The young are very dark above, with more distinct cinnamon-color on the belly in the young of some specimens than in the adults.

On the prairies in Northern Illinois and Southern Wisconsin, the Arvicola austerus exists in greater abundance than any other native mammal, and far exceeds in numbers the other species of arvicolae found here. The extent of its distribution is not yet known, but it will probably be found throughout the neighboring prairie regions. It never has, within my knowledge, been found in the woods. It frequents both dry and wet land, preferring the latter. In summer, these animals inhabit low, wet prairies, in great numbers, digging burrows and forming nests in them, as well as on the ground among the grass. In autumn, they retire to higher ground, to spend the winter, being driven out of their summer homes by the heavy fall rains. Their winter burrows on the uncultivated prairie are often in old ant-hills, or, if not, the earth thrown out of them forms little hillocks. They are not very deep, seldom over six inches or a foot, but are remarkable for the numerous and complicated chambers and side-passages of which they are composed. In one of these chambers, considerably enlarged, is placed the nest, formed of fine, dry grass. It is globular, from four to six inches in diameter, and with but a small cavity in the center, which is entered by a very narrow opening on one side. This burrow and nest are occupied in winter, and in it at least the first litter of young is produced in spring; but, in the summer and fall, these meadow-mice may be found in similar nests in the grass above ground, in which the young are often, if not usually, brought forth. Nests formed under the snow in winter are also occupied by them. From the burrows, innumerable runways traverse the neighborhood, intersecting those from other burrows, thus forming a complete network so that often scarcely a square yard can be found in an acre not crossed by one or more of these tracks. The runways of one pair may sometimes be traced five or ten rods on every side. These roads are not only formed for use in winter, when the ground is covered with snow, but are also employed as highways in summer. They are made above ground, by pressing down and gnawing off the grass, and the earth is often worn quite smooth and bare in those most used. The inhabitants can travel easily along them at all times, in search of food, being well concealed by the overarching grass. In Winter, these paths are formed on the ground, under the snow, as well as in the grass. The mice do not inhabit prairie pastures, where the grass is eaten close and affords them no cover.

This species is exceedingly prolific. Five young are most commonly produced at birth; but the number varies from three to six. They are brought forth from early in April till October; and, in one instance, I found suckling young in the middle of November. Of the number of litters produced in a year, I am unable to form a certain estimate. The young, though not generally found attached to the mother’s teats, as is the case with some other species, are at times observed in that situation; and a female was seen to carry three half-grown young a distance of several feet in this manner. As soon as they are able to take care of themselves, they leave the mother. In summer, the old males do not live with the females and young, but are generally with the females in spring, although an old male has been found in November with a female and her suckling young.

In their home on the prairie, the natural food of these animals is the grasses, with their roots and seeds, as well as those of some other plants. Various roots, indeed, form the largest portion, and usually comprise the store of provisions collected for their winter subsistence.

Mr. Job Galloway, of Northfield, informs me that, while mowing in a low prairie, inhabited during summer by this species, he observed a small garter-snake passing rapidly through the grass, with a young meadow-mouse, partly swallowed, in its mouth. The low squeak uttered by the latter attracted his attention. Presently, an old meadow-mouse emerged from the tall grass in pursuit of the snake. Stopping an instant, as if to listen for the cry of her young, she again pursued, and finally overtook the snake, which she unhesitatingly attacked. The snake stopped, disgorged his prey, and defended himself by striking his assailant, which appeared to be beating him, when he was killed by Mr. Galloway.

Upon examining, in November, the burrow of a pair of these meadow-mice, situated on the wild prairie, I found the excavation to have been recently enlarged. The nest was placed near the center of the burrow; and at one side, and in the deepest part of the excavation, was the store of winter provisions. This consisted of 5 or 6 quarts of roots, chiefly the round tubers of two species of spike-flower (Liatris), which grow abundantly in the vicinity, with a few roots of Helianthus, and various grasses, and several bulbs of wild onions. By tracing carefully the numerous and extensive paths which run in every direction from the burrow, I observed where the inmates had procured their food. The large fleshy root of the rosin-weed, or compass-pant, (Silphium laciniatum), appeared to have been eaten very freely in autumn, at least. The root of this interesting prairie plant is sometimes a foot in length, and an inch or two in diameter at the top. To obtain it, they had burrowed down alongside, quite to the bottom, eating out the entire soft parts. Though so much eaten, none of it was found in their burrows.

The prairie meadow-mouse is not a gregarious animal naturally; and, when more than one pair is found together in fields, it is where they have all been alike attracted by the food and shelter offered by the situation. Though their burrows are sometimes quite near each other on the prairies, this is only when they are very abundant. Two pairs never occupy the same hole.

In cultivated fields, the habits of this species are somewhat changed. When corn fields are near, they flock to them in autumn in great abundance; and, wherever a corn shock is to be found, a pair takes possession of it, digging under it a more simple burrow than in the prairie or meadows. Besides the nest in this burrow, another is formed among the corn stalks, above or at the surface of the ground, and is chiefly occupied during mild weather, the inmates retiring to the burrow in extreme cold. Frequently a corn shock will be temporarily inhabited by those having burrows at some distance. A quantity of corn is carried into the winter burrow under the shock, in spring, as well as in autumn, in compliance with the inclination to collect stores of food at all seasons.

By looking in the fields the day next following the fall of snow, in November, I had an opportunity to observe something of what these arvicolae had been doing in the night. As there was scarcely an inch of snow, they had not generally travelled under it, as they do when it is deeper, by pushing it aside, mole-like, at the surface of the ground, but had moved on top, leaving their plain tracks. In a field containing shocks of corn, they could be traced not only to the shocks they inhabited, but to all others. Some were traced to burrows into which they had carried large stores of corn taken from shocks several yards distant, and others could be tracked for ten or fifteen rods across the field, to where they had entered the grass at the edge of the prairie, having come from their burrows to feed upon the corn. Wherever there was grass or weeds, though only two or three inches high, they had moved under it, in preference to going on top; and even on clear ground, where the snow was drifted to the depth of two or three inches, they had passed beneath, leaving it unbroken above. This illustrates, not only the smoothness of their gliding motions, but also their disinclination to travel by springing over high objects. In moving over plowed ground, they did not jump clear across from one ridge of the furrow to the other, but ran part of the way down one side and up on the other. When traveling on the open ground, they moved by short jumps of from four to eight inches. Sometimes, they ran or trotted, appearing always to move in this way in their runways in the grass; and, in fact, this is the gait most natural to them. When caged specimens are liberated on a smooth surface, they glide off at this gait with great rapidity, never jumping, but rather running around small objects; though, on the whole, they show more activity than their forms would seem to indicate, springing readily to some distance when so disposed.

I have often kept specimens of this species in cages for a short time. They soon became reconciled to confinement, and took food from my hands. When placed in wooden boxes, they generally made no attempt to gnaw out, though, when they did begin to use their teeth in this manner, they would sometimes cut their way through an inch of board.

In confinement, they ate all kinds of grain and vegetables, including the bark of the apple, pine, and other trees. The stems and leaves of grasses, with pansies, pinks, and other plants from the garden, were also eaten indiscriminately. They also managed to gnaw through the shells of hickory-nuts, though such a thing as a nut could never have been seen by them before. Raw, fresh meat of any kind was eagerly devoured. In short, they were omnivorous. The amount of food consumed by some specimens was astonishing. Three ate, in twenty-four hours, besides other food, the germs from all the kernels on a good-sized ear of corn. At another time, a piece of carrot, measuring over a cubic inch, was eaten by two specimens in one night; though they ate corn, grass, and meat the previous and following days. They drank a good deal of water, soon perishing when left long without it, or some moist food. In drinking, they sometimes lapped, but oftener thrust the nose into the water and moved the jaws as in masticating. When eating, they grasped the food in their fore-paws, or sometimes held some particles in one paw, while standing upon their hind-feet, not erect on the haunches, but resting on the foot, (tarsus,) with the back-bone arched, and the body leaning forward. This position was also frequently assumed when they were not eating and they often stood quite erect, upon the tarsi, or toes, alone, to look about, or to examine anything held above them. In running, the toes only were placed upon the ground. The fore-paws are used as hands with all the facility of a squirrel, the food being grasped in them, and turned about at pleasure. Upon holding a of grass near one, he seized it with his paws, and, biting off small pieces with his incisors, chewed and swallowed them rapidly. As I pulled it gently, he grasped it more firmly; and, as I continued to pull, he reached up an inch or two, and cut off the stem with his teeth. A piece of the dry, outer covering of this getting into his mouth, he held that which he was eating from in one paw, and with the other quite readily drew out the unpalatable part, without ceasing to masticate. When an ear of corn was placed in the cage, each one would seize a kernel with his incisors, and, bracing his feet against the ear, wrench it out by pulling to one side. In eating, the food was cut into very small pieces by the incisors, before being ground by the molar teeth. They sometimes attempted to crush pieces of meat or vegetables, half the size of a pea, with their molars, but, taking them into their paws again, would always cut them smaller with their front teeth. When the bottom of the cage was filled with earth, they would soon burrow in it. In digging, they would scratch rapidly with the fore-feet several times, and then throw back the earth to a greater distance with the hind-feet. The nose was much used to push the dirt aside, which was also frequently loosened with the teeth. As the hole grew deeper, and was dug horizontally, they sometimes turned over on the back, to dig in that position. In removing the earth from a burrow of some extent, they came out backwards, scratching back the earth, with both hind and fore-feet, as they came.

The ferocity and exceedingly carnivorous propensities exhibited by some specimens of this little rodent are truly astonishing. Adult specimens recently captured and placed together often kill and devour each other, mothers even eating their young. One evening I placed in a large cage two old males taken in different burrows. In the course of the night, much fighting and crying was heard, and the next morning one was found to have been killed and partly devoured by his companion. The other was supplied with corn and fresh beef, both of which he ate; and in the course of the forenoon, a half-grown house-mouse was placed alive in the cage. This, without provocation, he at once attacked, as if in great rage, uttering his usual cry of anger, with his hair erected and bristling. In fighting, he sprang upon the mouse, striking with his fore-feet, at the same time snapping quickly with his teeth, and then springing nimbly back. Finally, he seized the mouse by the rump with his incisors, and thus broke his back-bone. After this, the latter, which had fought as well as he could, ceased to resist, when the meadow-mouse, catching him in his teeth, threw him forcibly to some distance, and continued to strike, bite, and toss him about until he was dead. His anger then appeared to subside as rapidly as it had risen, and a few minutes he was observed placidly eating corn. The old males were always very pugnacious, biting and striking at anything thrust towards them. When much teased in this way, they sometimes turned on their backs, snapping with their teeth, and striking with all four feet. When enraged, they uttered a low, harsh, creaking note, resembling that of a very young puppy. If hurt, their voices were clearer and sharper. Sometimes they chattered their teeth in anger. The females were not so pugnacious, and were more silent; seldom fighting or crying out in anger when teased. They were equally as carnivorous, however, as the males. Like most arvicolae, this species takes to the water boldly, and swims and dives readily.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

The binomial name Arvicola austerus [Le Conte, 1853] is now considered to be an invalid junior synonym of Microtus ochrogaster [Wagner, 1842].

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Prairie Vole’.

For more information on the Prairie Vole, see:

Mammalian Species № 355: DOI:10.2307/3504103
ITIS Report for TSN 180312

Southern Gray or Carolina Squirrel

[Photo 6]

Sciurus carolinensis [Gmelin, 1788]

Description.—Size somewhat smaller than the migratory northern gray and black-squirrels. It is of a rusty-gray color above; on the belly, it is pure white; the feet and face are somewhat tinged with rufous. These colors do not vary, and the species may thus at once be distinguished from Sciurus migratorius, wherever it abounds.

This species is a Southern squirrel, and is most abundant in some of the southern states. Audubon and Bachman say it is not numerous in Alabama and Mississippi, and that it has not been seen west of the Mississippi River. I have received specimens however, from Miss Helen Tennison, of Monticello, Mississippi, who informs me that it is common in the woods along Pearl River. It is found in Virginia and Southern Ohio. In Southern Illinois and Indiana, it is exceedingly abundant. At Cairo, in this state, I saw specimens which had been shot in Kentucky, and I was told that it was abundant in the western part of that state as well as in south-eastern Missouri. It doubtless exists throughout Kentucky and Tennessee. Dr. Hoy informs me that he saw it, in considerable numbers, through Central Missouri, along the Missouri and Osage Rivers. In the more heavily timbered districts, along the Mississippi and Illinois Rivers, this squirrel abounds, even in Northern Illinois. I believe it is never found in the prairie groves nor oak openings; but in the prairie regions, in the northern counties of this state, it is occasionally met with in heavy timber on the low river-bottoms, or in those skirting Lake Michigan. In this locality, it is known among hunters as the “Silver-gray Squirrel.”

The Carolina squirrel delights in the heavy timber on low bottom lands. It even finds a favorite home in the deep shade of cypress swamps, where the sombre drapery, formed by the hanging Tillandsia, gives them a dark and sad appearance, but which, wonderfully, is enlivened by the numbers of squirrels that run about the trees, and leap from limb to limb, or sit perched upon the branches, saucily eyeing the traveller, who, delighted by their merry activity in this gloomy place, pauses to observe them. In Southern Illinois, where this and the fox-squirrel are the only species found, it is much more numerous in the swamps and river bottoms than on the high ridges.

This squirrel is very generally confounded with the Sciurus migratorius of the North, and naturalists have made much confusion by falling into this error. DeKay, in the “Natural History of New York,” calls the migratory squirrel Sciurus carolinensis; and some other naturalists still persist in considering the two identical. A little attention to the habits of each would convince any one of the propriety of considering them distinct.

The food of the Carolina squirrel is much the same as that of the two species already described. They bury nuts and acorns in the leaves, and late in winter feed largely upon buds, being particularly fond apparently of those of the soft maple and the elm. Like the others, they incur the wrath of the farmer by their ravages in the corn field, where they devour the grain on the stalk and carry off whole ears to the woods.

From three to six young are produced at a birth by this species. Two, and possibly sometimes three litters, are brought forth in a year. They are rarely produced in the nests of leaves.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

The squirrel being referenced here is the nominative subspecies when trinomial nomenclature is used, Sciurus carolinensis carolinensis [Gmelin, 1788].

The author notes that in his day, some naturalists considered the Migratory Squirrel Sciurus migratorius to be conspecific with Sciurus carolinensis. That is now the overwhelmingly accepted consensus. The two are the same species, although they are classified as different subspecies, with what was formerly known as Sciurus migratorius now split into several subspecies of Sciurus carolinensis.

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Eastern Gray Squirrel’. Although multiple subspecies are recognized, common names at the subspecies level do not appear to be used in most current literature.

For more information on the Eastern Gray Squirrel, see:

Mammalian Species № 480: DOI:10.2307/3504224
ITIS Report for TSN 180175 (S. carolinensis)
ITIS Report for TSN 930431 (S. c. carolinensis)

Prairie Squirrels, or Spermophiles

These are with great propriety called “Prairie Squirrels,” for their true home is on the prairie, where they replace the “arboreal” squirrels, from which they differ in organization, to suit their necessarily different mode of life. While the true squirrels are designed to live in trees, and to subsist upon their fruits, the spermophiles are fitted to inhabit the grassy plains which cover much of the western part of our Union, their food being the prairie plants with their roots and seeds. The form of these squirrels is adapted only to locomotion on the ground. The body is thick and heavy, with short legs, and, in place of the long toes and sharp-hooked nails, by which the arboreal squirrels cling to the trees so readily, they have shorter toes with longer and straighter nails, for digging burrows in the earth. The long, flexible and bushy tails, which aid the squirrels in their bold leaps, and keep them warm in their holes in winter, would here be useless, and soon worn ragged by dragging through their burrows. The spermophiles, therefore, have smaller tails, that are carried straight behind them. They have cheek-pouches, in which to carry food; and two species, at least, convey roots, seeds, &c. to their burrows to be eaten.

In winter, there would be little food or shelter for them on the frozen and snow-covered prairies; and so the spermophiles make one long night of it, and sleep away the season of frost. The peculiar state of torpor in which these and some other rodents, as well as a few carnivorous mammals, pass the winter, is an admirable provision in the economy of Nature. At the approach of severe cold, in autumn, the prairie squirrel retires to its burrow, the entrances to which are tightly closed with earth, to exclude the frost. In the large nest of grass he curls himself up, with his head against the abdomen, and falls into a state of torpor, out of which he does not awaken until the return of warm weather in spring. In this state, he takes no nourishment, whatever, nor does he move.

If cut or bruised, he exhibits no signs of feeling; and to all external appearances seems dead. Respiration and the circulation of the blood are carried on very imperfectly; but slight oxygenation of the blood takes place, and little heat is generated—the body being cold. There is no secretion nor excretion, and very little waste of tissues occurs; and thus the necessity for food is obviated. From this state, he is at once revived to activity by the simple application of heat. Placed in the cold, he again becomes torpid. It is to be observed that the species, which passes the winter thus in profound torpor, if removed to a warmer climate, or if kept in a warm room, will remain active during winter. Thus we see how, in the perfect laws of Nature, it is ordered, that the hibernating animals shall fall into this state of torpor only when they would suffer from cold and want of food, if active.

These, like the true squirrels, are strictly diurnal. Most of the species are inclined to be gregarious, while some live together in large companies. The flesh of several is said to be palatable, though I am not aware that either of our two prairie-squirrels is eaten, in this vicinity. Two species have rendered themselves obnoxious to our prairie farmers.

Squirrels

The true squirrel is arboreal. His home is in the trees, and his legitimate food their fruits and buds. Should he go to the ground, it is only in search of food; and, this obtained, he returns to his airy dwelling-place. Here, in summer, he builds him a nest of leaves taken from the branches at hand, and in a hole in the same tree, or in one that he can attain by springing from branch to branch without going to the ground, he has a more secure retreat, to which he can retire during inclement weather, or escape the attacks of an enemy, and in which the young are generally reared.

This class of squirrels possesses a muscular but light and graceful form, with the toes long and the nails strong and sharp, by which they are enabled to climb trees and take long leaps among the branches with wonderful ease. In these leaps, they are also aided by their large and bushy tails, which serve as rudders to steer by. They use their fore feet as hands, seizing their food with them, and stand upon their hind feet, when eating. On the ground, they either run or move by springs made mainly by the hind-legs. Unlike most of the order, they move about by day and keep in their retreats at night, to which they also retire for a few hours during the middle of the day. Though their food is properly vegetable, squirrels are known to eat insects. By a slighter departure from their natural food, they exhibit a fondness for corn, and more rarely wheat and other grains, which is highly prejudicial to their good standing in a community of farmers. In fact, these animals are frequently much more injurious than is generally known. In certain districts, whole fields of corn are destroyed by them at times, while it is a common thing to find considerable tracts lying near the woods not worth harvesting, because of their depredations. So serious was the result of their ravages at one time in the Eastern States that, as related by Pennant, in the year 1749, £8,000 were paid out of the treasury of Pennsylvania in premiums for the destruction of squirrels. The premium for each being 3 pence, would show that the enormous number of six hundred and forty thousand were killed in one year, besides the vast numbers for which no rewards were claimed, and those also which were otherwise destroyed.

In some States, parties for grand hunts are occasionally organized in autumn, the hunters forming into two companies, each of which endeavors to outdo the other in the number of squirrels brought in, and the losing party forfeiting the expense of the evening’s entertainment at the wayside or village inn. These hunts are kept up from one to three days, and the quantities of squirrels sometimes shot—without estimating those purchased for the occasion by eager but unfair members of the company—would seem incredible to persons not residing in localities where they abound.

Squirrels at times form a valuable addition to our food. There is a foolish prejudice existing among many against eating them; but a young spuirrel properly cooked makes a delicious morsel, and old ones are far from unpalatable , when fat. Their flesh is certainly more healthful and delicate than that of so unclean an animal as the hog, which, nevertheless frequently is preferred. Great numbers are sold in our city markets, and usually at low prices. In winter, thousands of migratory Carolina and fox-squirrels are bought up by purchasers of provisions throughout Indiana, Michigan, Illinois, and forwarded to Chicago, where the marketmen retail them at 12½ cents each. The skins of our American species are of no value in commerce, their fur being little esteemed and seldom used.

Squirrels probably do not suffer much from the attacks of wild animals. Man is their worst enemy. Wild-cats, martins, and some of the larger hawks and snakes sometimes capture the young, and more rarely the old ones. They are occasionally infested by the larvæ of a species of œstrus[1] , which must give them much annoyance. These grubs, or “warbles,” are found living in the skin, in abscesses formed by their presence, usually about the shoulders and such other parts as the squirrel cannot reach with his teeth.

Squirrels are readily domesticated, making pleasing and intelligent pets. In confinement, they exhibit their usual activity; and, indeed, if not permitted exercise, they often pine and die. Cages are hence usually provided with revolving wheels, in which the captives soon learn to turn, and from which they derive even more enjoyment than do the spectators by this substitute for their natural exercise.

[1] œstrus here refers to a parasitical fly in the family Oestridae.

Striped and Spotted Prairie-Squirrel

[Plate VIII.b, Photo 10]

Spermophilus tridecemlineatus [Mitchill, 1788][1]

Description.—Length of adult male, in September, from nose to root of tail, 7 inches; tail, (vertebræ,) 3⅝ inches; tail to tip of longest hair, 4¼ inches; hind-foot 1½ inches; On the back and sides there are nine stripes of a dark brown color, with a row of yellowish dots along each of the five central stripes, which are the broadest and most distinct. Alternating with these brown stripes, are eight narrow lines of yellowish-gray; thus making seventeen in all, which shows Mitchill’s name to not be very characteristic. The lower lines are indistinct, and in some specimens, cannot be traced. The under parts of the body are yelllowish-brown.

This little animal, so well known on our prairies, resembles the common chipmuck (Tamias striatus), and is of about the same size, or a little longer. It abounds in the prairies of Michigan, Wisconsin, Minnesota, Iowa, Northern Missouri, Middle and Northern Illinois, and Northern Indiana. It is only found in the northern edge of Missouri. In Illinois, it is most abundant in the northern part of the State; and it does not exist at all below latitude thirty-nine degrees, if it does as far south as that. It is not found east of the prairie regions, nor oak openings, of Indiana and Michigan, except rarely in the northeastern corner of Ohio. At the North, Richardson found it towards latitude fifyt-five degrees, in the British Possessions; it has been seen as far west as Fort Laramie, on Platte River. Audubon and Bachman state that it is found abundantly on the Upper Missouri, and that it is said to extend along the prairies east of the Rocky Mountains into Mexico.

In Iowa, Wisconsin, and Northern Illinois where this animal is abundant and much complained of by farmers, it is universally called “gopher.” The true gopher (Pseudostoma bursarius)[2] being also found in Iowa and Illinois, the two animals are frequently confounded; and such is the profound contempt of some farmers for any systematic study of natural history, that, though repeated descriptions of both these animals have been published in various agricultural journals, they go on correcting each other’s statements, after a fashion, in preference to learning first what they are writing about. One, who knows only the true gopher, burrows of which are miles in length, very naturally laughs at another for saying he drowns out hundreds of gophers, (meaning prairie-squirrels,) by pouring a pailful or two of water into a burrow; while the latter must be very careless, to state that gophers cut the roots of trees, gnaw vegetables, and injur fields by throwing up hills. The Pseudostoma undoubtedly has the best right to the name of “gopher,” and should retain it. Our farmers would obviate needless and frequent confusion, if they would not apply the same name to the present species, for which the designation “Striped Prairie Squirrel” would be far more appropriate; and which, in fact, is highly characteristic, being in itself a description of the animal. To call it “Ground Squirrel,” as is sometimes done, is bad, because the Tamias striatus is well known as the “Striped Ground Squirrel.” In Northern Illinois, I have heard the German farmers very generally call it “Fence Mouse,” which name they also apply to the Tamias striatus.

This species is emphatically a prairie animal. It never inhabits timber lands when there is prairie in the vicinity. Though it may be found in oak openings, it is never in heavy timber; and, when living in these openings, it is always most abundant on the edges of open ground, or where the trees are most scattering.

I am not aware that this prairie-squirrel ever inhabits ravines,[♦] in preference to level ground, though Spermophilus franklinii[3] sometimes appears fond of burrowing in banks. The favorite habitation of this species is on dry prairie knolls. It is naturally gregarious, and though never observed living in such great companies as the prairie-dog, twenty, or sometimes even fifty or a hundred may be found within the area of an acre, two burrows being frequently within a few feet of each other, though one is never inhabited by more than a pair. In passing near a knoll inhabited by them, numbers may be seen standing upright at the entrance of their burrows, so straight and motionless as to be easily mistaken for as many sticks. But, as you approach one, he will disappear, by a movement so rapid that he can scarcely be followed by the eye; and, if it were not for the whistling chatter accompanying his disappearance, you might think your vision had deceived you, and that nothing had been there. But upon stepping back several rods, it is more than likely that he will have resumed his position before you are aware of it. If you remain close to his hole, he will only thrust out his head and eye you suspiciously.

The striped spermophile leaves its burrow with great caution, and only for a short distance. At the slightest alarm it silently glides back through the grass, yet with great rapidity, keeping close to the ground and never leaping. Its burrow reached, unless closely pursued, it stops for a moment at the entrance, sitting upright on the tarsi, and then suddenly pops into the hole, uttering several quick, clear, whisteling notes. Unless it has been very much alarmed, it ill always thrust out its head again to reconnoitre; and boys, taking advantage of this practice, often catch these animals by slipping a noose arranged over the hole, the moment one has entered. When one is shot near his burrow, the body can seldom be secured, for, like the prairie-dog, unless cut to pieces by the shot, he will manage to tumble into his hole.

Before the production of the young, in May or June, the old male leaves the female, and appears to lead a solitary and more or less wandering life, digging a temporary burrow, or occupying a deserted one for a few days, wherever he may take up his abode. These summer burrows may often be found, and sometimes are of considerable extent; several of those which were examined were more than 20 feet in length, being simple galleries from six inches to a foot below the surface—deeper in sandy soil—opening at both ends, with the nest placed in a small side-chamber; others were of much less extent, sometimes with but one entrance, and sometimes without nests. The winter burrow, in which the pair hibernate and the female brings forth her young, is deeper and more complicated, having always two entrances or more. In this, in a side-chamber of suitable size, excavated above the level of the rest of the burrow, is a large spherical nest of soft grass, entered by an opening on one side. This nest is sometimes of the size of a half bushel, the interior being generally lined with softer material than the outside. The young are produced at the end of May or early in June. I have observed from five to nine brought forth at a birth, and I am informed of two instances in which ten were found in a nest; but the number is variable, the usual number being six or seven. The young at birth are naked, blind, and remarkably embryonic. Dr. Hoy, who observed them in confinement, says that they have no hair on the body before they are twenty days old, and that the eyes do not open till the thirteenth day. They continue to require the nourishment and care of the mother for a much longer period than most rodents. During summer, they begin to dig shallow burrows, and leave her before winter, to shift for themselves. Hibernating mammals require to be in good condition when they retire to winter-quarters, which the females could scarcely be, did they rear young late in the season. This spermophile and probably the rest of the genus produce but one litter of young a year.

The natural food of the striped spermophile is the grasses, with their seeds and roots, as well as those of various other herbaceous plants, and even the most minute seeds of annuals. Mice and insects are also known to form a part of their food. Many of our farmers suppose that this animal feeds, in winter, upon stores of provisions laid up in its hole for that season; for, though it spends the winter in a state of profound torpor, it collects food in its burrow. This is done in spring and summer, as well as in autumn. Considerable stores of grain, seeds, roots, &c., are found thus collected, in large side-chambers excavated for their reception in the burrow. Corn, wheat, and oats are stored up, when taken from the newly-planted fields in spring, with buckwheat and winter wheat later in the season, as well as heads of grain taken from the edges of the fields in harvest time. I have seen more than a quart of crab-apples taken from the burrow of one which had carried them several rods from a tree. George and Frank Kennicott inform me that they observed one, the burrow of which was near a lone burr-oak, on the prairie, to carry great quantities of acorns into his hole; and another was killed by them, the cheek-pouches of which were crammed with the dry ovaries of a prairie plant, the seeds of which were exceedingly minute. From this, it would appear that the striped spermophile at all seasons carries portable articles of food to its burrow to be eaten. He certainly takes no food from the time he first becomes torpid, in autumn, until he again becomes active, late in the following spring. In Northern Illinois, these animals generally go into winter-quarters late in October, usually retiring at the first appearance of hard frost, though a few keep out longer; and I have observed several, in warm weather, as late as the 10th of November, after the ground had been frozen an inch deep, and there had been constant frost for several days. In spring, they rarely leave their burrows before the frost is fully out of the ground. To Mr. William Bebb, of Fountaindale, Winnebago county, Illinois, I am indebted for the following dates of this spermophile’s first appearance in spring, as noted in the meteorological register of Mr. Edward Bebb: “1851, April 10th; 1852, April 11th; 1853, April 2d; 1854, March 29th; 1855, April 12th.”

Among farmers, this spermophile has a bad reputation, in consequence of its injuring corn fields by digging up the newly-planted seed, in spring. Persons residing on newly-broken prairie inform me that they sometimes suffer severely from the prairie-squirrels. It is said that large corn fields have to be replanted, where they have been at work, while, in some districts, every corn field is seriously injured by them. No sooner is the corn planted, than they begin to work at the edges of the field next to their burrows. They show much intelligence in following the rows, sometimes digging up every hill for several rods, and this before, as well as after the corn has sprouted. They are industrious, and take up a great deal of corn in a day, which, apparently, is always carried to the burrow. In such districts, farmers agree that their injury to corn fields is on so extensive a scale as to render the destruction of the prairie-squirrels a matter of serious interest. They also do more or less injury, by digging up garden seeds, such as peas, melons, &c., and, though rarely, are more seriously injurious, by destroying apple and osage orange seeds in nurseries. I am not aware, however, that they are ever accused of gnawing bark, destroying growing vegetables, or, in fact, of injuring the farmer in any other way than by devouring grain and seeds. In consequence of this reputation for mischievous habits in the corn field, farmers all appear to think it a good deed to kill a spermophile. But they should not be too hasty; for, as far as the present species is concerned, there is something to be heard in its favor. In the Patent Office Report for 1853, page 68, Dr. Hoy has shown that this animal feeds upon mice and insects, when in captivity, and he further informs me that he has examined burrows in which the numbers of the skins of meadow-mice found sufficiently proved the appetite exhibited by his caged specimens to be natural. Those observed in captivity, killed and devoured mice in the same manner as the weasel, showing themselves to be adepts at this mode of procuring food. One would spring upon a mouse savagely, uttering a low snarl, and despatch it by biting its neck, after which the top of the skull was taken off, the brains licked out, and the blood sucked, the body not being devoured when there was an abundant supply. There can be no doubt that meadow-mice and insects are largely eaten by these animals whenever they can be obtained; and the high probability is, that their good offices in the destruction of these, far more than counterbalance their occasional injury to corn fields. I doubt their being so very injurious in long-cultivated farms. The first few crops of corn planted on newly-broken prairie, inhabited by striped spermophiles, suffer from their ravages; and so a hue and cry is raised against them, and their actual depredations are much exaggerated. This animal disappears before the plow, and, as it will never leave its burrow for any great distance, it does not generally invade well-cultivated fields, nor attack corn except at the sides of the field next to wild prairies or meadows inhabited by it. In Northern Illinois, I have observed large corn fields, raised on farms in the meadows of which this spermophile abounds, where, if it does any harm at all, it is so inconsiderable as not to be noticed. Dr. Hoy says that in a large neighborhood in Southern Wisconsin, where these spermophiles are very numerous, he knows of but one farmer who kills them, nor is he able to hear that they do any considerable injury.

When, in newly-cultivated districts, it becomes necessary to exterminate the striped spermophile, it can be done with ease. It is readily trapped or shot, and a few bucketfuls of water will always drown one out of its hole. But in killing this animal, let farmers consider whether they are not destroying a friend. Let all observe critically how many mice, grasshoppers, &c., it destroys, and then treat it accordingly. This species suffers but little, when at all, from rapacious animals. It leaves its burrow with so much caution, and is so constantly on the alert, as to be rarely exposed to their attacks. Hawks are not observed to catch, nor even to hunt for them.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

In 2009, this subgenus Ictidomys was elevated to full genus status resulting in the binomial name Ictidomys tridecemlineatus [Mitchill, 1788] for this species. Numerous subspecies are currently recognized.

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Thirteen-Lined Ground Squirrel’.

For more information on the Thirteen-Lined Ground Squirrel, see:

Generic Revision in the Holarctic Ground Squirrel Genus Spermophilus (Helgen, 2009): DOI:10.1644/07-MAMM-A-309.1
ITIS Report for TSN 930308

[♦] In the Patent Office Report for 1853, Dr. P. R. How, of Racine, Wisconsin, gave a highly interesting and original account of this animal. In that article, as printed, this species is stated to be abundant in the ravines of Wisconsin, but he informs me that this is an accidental error, “ravines” being printed where “prairies” was intended to be expressed.

[1] The author gave an incorrect spelling of Spermophilus tredecimlineatus with an incorrect authority spelling of [Mitchell].

The correct spelling of Spermophilus tridecemlineatus with the correct authority spelling [Mitchill, 1821] is used in the article in place of the mistake.

[2] Current nomenclature for the Plains Pocket Gopher is Geomys bursarius [Shaw, 1800].

[3] Current nomenclature for the Gray Prairie-Squirrel (Franklin’s Ground Squirrel) is Poliocitellus franklinii [Sabine, 1822].

To Do List

This digital book currently does an adequate job at representing the original content of the author.

There are however improvements that will be hopefully made.

With the exception of potential legal and WCAG level A and AA issues, published updates to this digital book will not happen more than once every six months.

This digital publication needs proper Content Accessibility testing so that any existing WCAG level A or AA issues can be immediately fixed and any level AAA issues can be fixed when possible. Content Accessibility issues can be reported at the github issues page. Actual certified testing will require budget which will require donations. I have not yet received an estimate for certified testing cost.
Glossary entries need to be made for every term that could be confusing to a student in junior high school. If you aware of a term that needs a glossary entry, please feel free to file a bug report (issue) at the github issues page.

The reproduced plates from the original article are not of the quality I would like and they may have legal issues as they were extracted from a Google Books PDF scan.

The original article is in the public domain but the way U. S. copyright law works, a new copyright is assigned to a photograph or scan of another work.

I managed to find an original copy of the publication on eBay at a cost of $48.66 USD shipped, purchased on August 01, 2020. There is a second article with plates in that same volume that I will be transcribing to ePub in the future. This article has 20 illustration on 10 plates, the second article (Avian) has 32 illustrations on 32 plates, so between both articles the cost comes to just under a dollar per illustration, not including my time, and assuming all the plates are in a usable/restorable condition.

The book has not arrived yet at initial publication time, but I will be able to use it to replace some if not all of the plates from the Google Books scanned plates with higher quality digitally restored scans that do not have any question with respect to copyright usage.

The eBay seller did note there is some foxing (age related yellow-brownish spotting) of the plates. This will require some digital image cleanup work and as such will require quite a bit of time before a version of this digital book with improved plates is available.

It is possible I will also convert the plates to SVG for better scaling, which will take additional time.

The illustrators for the original plates need to be identified so that proper credit can be given. This may be easier once the original copy arrives.

Obtain quality photographs as specified in the Needed Photographs appendix section that follows.

Whenever possible, I do attempt to acquire existing quality photographs that have an Open Access compatible license, but I am somewhat picky when it comes to quality.

Whenever possible, I do attempt to provide photographs myself. Unfortunately with this publication, I am a long ways away from where many of the animals described in this paper are found, and my own photographs frequently do not meet my quality expectations. I must concede that many high school students with an artistic eye and no formal photography training take better photographs than I do.

When suitable freely available photographs have not been found, I would like to be able to offer a $50 bounty to the photographer for a suitable photograph—especially if the photographer is a life sciences student or recent graduate—but I do not currently have that kind of budget. Financial donations specified for that purpose would help.

If you do have photographic ability and access to the species in the list, please contact me but be aware I can not pay you unless donations for that purpose have come in.

The ePub specification allows for phonetic markup. At this time, ePub viewers do not support this part of the specification, but hopefully in the near future they will. Phonetic pronunciation of words that are likely to be mispronounced by Text-To-Speech (TTS) synthesizers need to be added. Some already have been added, but a careful analysis of all content needs to be done to identify additional cases where phonetic markup is warranted.
At some point I would like to provide a Spanish translation, Spanish is spoken at home among many school-aged children in much of America. I do not expect this to happen for at least a year.

White-Footed Prairie-Mouse

[Plate XI.a, Photo 15]

Mus bairdii [Hoy and Kennicott, 1857]

Description.—Length of the adult male from nose to root of tail, 2⅛ inches; tail, (vertebræ,) 1⅞ inches; hind-foot, ¾ of an inch. Head and body of a large male, 3¾ inches; tail, 2 inches. In another specimen, the head and body, 3 and three-sixteenths inches; tail, 1¾ inches. In spring, the hairs on the upper parts are plumbeous at the base, tipped with ashy and yellowish-brown; a few longer hairs, entirely black, interspersed. The tips of most of the hairs deepen into black along the back, giving a broad, black stripe, when the hair lies flat. In some specimens, this stripe is not so dark as in others, but is quite distinct in all, while in some it is pitch-black. On the upper lip, and entire under parts of the body and legs, the hairs are plumbeous at the base, tipped with pure white. The cheeks and lower edges of the color of the upper parts, are yellowish, forming a border between the colors of the belly and back. There is a distinct line of demarcation between this yellow border and the white belly. On each side of the root of the tail is a bright brownish-yellow spot, formed by the termination of the yellowish line on the side. The hairs immediately about the root of the tail are ashy-brown. The ears, upper part of the tail, and a distinct spot on the top of the fore-foot, are brownish-black. The nails and toes of all the feet, and the tops of the fore-feet, back to the blackish spot, are pure, creamy-white. In some specimens, the the hind-foot is white nearly back to the heel; in others, it is ashy-brown along the top, and white at the sides. The white of the under parts of the fore-arm extends sometimes quite, at others nearly, around on top, behind the blackish spot. The ears are as well clothed, and with as long hairs, as those of summer specimens of Mus leucopus; and the edges are whitish. The incisors are yellowish, those in the upper jaw darker than in the last-named species. The whiskers, situated anteriorly, are white, and those further back entirely black. The comparative number of white and black whiskers varies much in different specimens. When young, the upper parts are dark ashy-brown; darker along the back, and faintly tinged with yellowish on the cheeks, sides, and flanks. Like the preceding, this species varies a good deal in size, and somewhat in the shades of coloring. This mouse may be distinguished at once from its nearly allied congener the Mus michiganensis[1], of Audubon and Bachman, which Dr. Hoy has detected inhabiting the open woods near Racine, by its pure white belly, and by the distinct line of demarcation between the color of the belly and the yellowish-brown border on the sides. It will be very generally mistaken for the Mus leucopus, which it much resembles in form and color. Upon comparison, it may be readily distinguished, however, by its smaller size, much shorter tail, darker color, with usually a black dorsal stripe, more distinct than that in the Mus leucopus, and by its having the upper part of the tarsi ashy-brown instead of pure white, as in that species. Moreover, the one always inhabits the prairie, and the other the woods.

The Mus bairdii is found abundantly on the prairies in Northern Illinois and Southern Wisconsin; and Mr. Samuel Arny sent me a number of specimens from Bloomington, McLean county, Illinois, where, he informs me, it is common. It will probably be found in the neighboring prairie regions, where it is strictly an inhabitant, and replaces the Mus leucopus. I have never observed it in the woods, even near prairie fields in which it abounds. In Northern Illinois and Southern Wisconsin, this is a much more numerous species than the Mus leucopus. It is confined only to high ground, and it most abundant in cultivated fields.

Not having, on the prairies, the shelter found by its timber-loving cousins, in old stumps and trees, this species digs burrows. These are rather simple, with few or no side-passages, and often with but one entrance, the depth and extent being variable, but never great. The nest is small, composed of soft grass, &c.; it is spherical, and the small internal cavity is entered through a narrow opening on one side. In cultivated fields, the burrows are frequently dug at the roots of fruit-trees, the bark of which is often gnawed, sometimes causing great injury. In nurseries, fruit-trees are often taken up and “heeled in;” that is, laid down close together, with the roots placed in a trench, and then covered in such manner that they are kept safely in a very small space, and can be readily pulled out when desired. The loose earth among the roots of these, offers an inviting habitation to the mice; and, in nurseries infested by them, they will be found burrowing in almost every lot of trees thus buried, where they feed upon the bark of the roots, and thus cause serious damage. In the fall, they are often found in corn-shocks, making a nest among the stalks, though they do not often burrow under these as the arvicolæ. But, during winter, they may be tracked in corn-fields from their burrows to the neighboring corn-shocks, which they have visited for food. In spring, the young are always produced in burrows. During the summer, however, they are occasionally observed in nests, under bits of wood or bunches of hay, on the surface of the ground. In autumn, I have found nests of the young in small burrows only a few inches below the surface, or under an inverted sod. I have never observed more than one pair of adults occupying the same burrow; and, unlike the Mus leucopus, this species never appears to be gregarious.

This mouse must be very prolific.I have found the young in March and April, and observed two females, each with five young, apparently but a few days old, about the 10th of November, while they are found in every intervening month. In nearly every instance within my observation the number of young produced at a birth has been five. I once found six, and have at times, though rarely, seen three or four. The young are found attached to the teats, as in the species last described; and a female was seen to carry five for several rods in this way, jumping along rapidly, despite their weight. As soon as they are able to take care of themselves, the young leave the mother. In summer, I have several times found one apparently but a few weeks old, living alone in a nest made by himself. In spring, I have always found the old male living with the female and young; but during the summer, I have sometimes observed the male leading a solitary life, and the females and young in burrows by themselves. The food of this mouse, on the prairies, appears to be herbaceous plants, with their seeds; but I have been unable to see that it ever digs for roots. It is interesting to observe that this, like the Mus leucopus, seeks its food on top of the ground, running on the snow in winter in search of seeds, and collecting them in autumn instead of roots, when it travels as often by springing over the grass as by running through it, while the arvicolæ, both in summer and winter, dislike to leave the shelter of the herbage or snow, never being seen to travel over the grass, but always in runways so constructed as to afford concealment by grass or leaves; and their food consists largely, if not chiefly, of roots dug out of the ground. Were the Mus bairdii an inhabitant of the woods, it would doubtless be to some extent arboreal, which the arvicolæ never are. This mouse probably feeds more or less upon insects, as it is carnivorous in captivity; though some specimens are much less so than others. On one occasion, I captured a pair with five young, and placed them all in a cage well supplied with various kinds of vegetables and grain. The next day several of the young were killed and eaten, and in two or three days, they had all disappeared. Shortly afterwards, the male, which had been slightly injured, was found dead, and partly devoured by his rapacious spouse. After this, I fed my specimens with meat, as well as grain, which they ate; and, as long as they were supplied with it, they lived together harmless; but no sooner was this withheld, than the old ones, both male and female, devoured their young. Though all are more or less carnivorous, they are not generally so blood-thirsty as to devour each other or their young, when not supplied with flesh. Two, placed together in a cage, and observed carefully for several days, were never seen to fight, even when deprived of animal food. I several times noticed that, when one of these would pull a kernel of corn from the ear, his companion would also seize it with his teeth, and thus each would endeavor to draw it from the

[1] Junior synonym, now currently referred to by the binomial name Peromyscus leucopus [Rafinesque, 1818].

Wood Meadow-Mouse

[Plate XII.b]

Arvicola scalopsoides [Audubon and Bachman, 1841][1]

Description.—Head and body of the adult male, in November, nearly 3½ inches long; tail, nearly ¾ of an inch; hind-foot, ⅝ of an inch. Head, large; snout, blunt; ears, concealed by the fur; eyes, very small; fur on the back, soft, glossy and smooth; hairs, plumbeous at the base, broadly tipped with dark-brown on the back, and slightly tipped with white and reddish-brown on the belly. Young, color like that of the adult. This species is readily distinguished from the other arvicolae found in this vicinity, by its smaller size, glossy fur, large muzzle, small eyes, and very short tail. It is common in the woods in Northern Illinois and Southern Wisconsin, where it is less abundant, however, than the two preceding. This is probably the species mentioned under the name of Arvicola riparius, by Dr. Plummer, in Silliman’s Journal, as existing in Wayne county, Indiana.

Unlike the two species last described, this, so far as I have observed, lives exclusively in the woods, or in fields surrounded by timber, though it becomes more numerous in the clearing and prefers high ground. Its home, as noticed here, is under the leaves, and its mode of life brings strongly to mind the Sorex dekayi[2], with which, in fact, it is found in every locality in the woods where I have seen that shrew. Its runways are similar to those of the shrew; and I am inclined to think the tracks of the latter are much used by it. It is probable that the arvicolae may drive off the shrews, and take possession of their ready-made highways, as they are very pugnacious, and apparently able to beat the other, their eyes giving them much advantage over their sightless adversaries. They always travel under the leaves, apparently; and, in turning over logs, beneath which were their nests, I have observed that, in endeavoring to escape, they ran under instead of over the leaves, even where there were no paths; nor did they stop to hide in them; but ran off to some distance. When placed on the snow, it attempts to burrow into it, instead of running on top. This species is also more diurnal in its habits than the Arvicola austerus.

I have always found the nest of this arvicolae under logs or stumps, whether that of the female, with her young, in summer, or pairs in their winter-quarters in November. Those observed in fields always burrow under stumps or fences, instead of in the open ground. The nest in the woods is composed of leaves cut up into small fragments with fine grass. It is not placed in the under-ground burrow, but on the surface, being well protected by the log or roots above. The burrow is extensive, but not exceeding the length of the log or stump covering it. Numerous paths run in every direction from the burrow, under the leaves; they occasionally pass beneath the surface, and shallow holes are dug, as if in search of food, the earth being thrown out of these, whereby they are easily distinguished from the tracks of the shrew, which presses the earth aside in forming its track. By following these paths, I have observed where the meadow-mice fed upon the roots of grass and various other plants, often digging down several inches for them; and I have in several instances found the bark gnawed from the roots of briers, &c. Hickory-nuts, hazel-nuts, and acorns were also found partly eaten in their tracks. The acorns of the burr-oak and white-oak formed most of the stores collected in such burrows as I have examined. In one instance, I found the nest of a pair of this species in autumn, in part of a burrow occupied at the same time by chipmucks, and in which the latter had collected large stores of acorns and nuts.

This is the smallest of our rodents, and for its size, I know of no mammal more pugnacious than the males, at least. I placed one in a box with a specimen of Sorex dekayi, which it at once attacked. The shrew was courageous and never retreated, neither did he attempt to pursue the other to any distance. The meadow-mouse acted on the offensive, and made unprovoked attacks, the cage being large enough for both. He approached the shrew cautiously, and when within two or three inches sprang upon him, biting and striking with his feet, and then jumping back quickly, in fact fighting in the same manner as the Arvicola austerus. When he came near, and the shrew made the first attack, the meadow-mouse would rise upon his hind-feet, and strike with his fore ones, and snap rapidly with his teeth. Had the fight been allowed to continue, it is probable that the shrew would have been beaten; for, though much the stronger, and doubtless able to kill the meadow-mouse readily, if he could grapple with him, the latter was enabled, by his sudden springs, to inflict severe wounds, and exhaust his adversary, without being much hurt himself. The shrew constantly uttered his sharp, bird-like twitter; but the meadow-mouse fought in silence. This species, in fact, is always much more silent than the two preceding. When hurt, however, it utters low cry, softer and shorter than that of the Arvicola austerus. When a caged specimen was teased, it would become enraged, and bite fiercely at anything thrust at it.

Caged specimens of this species show less inclination to burrow than the two preceding. In eating, they do not hold the food up from the ground, but grasp it in the fore-paws, as it lies upon the surface, sitting meanwhile upon the hind-feet, yet resting in part upon the fore ones also. Is not this posture the necessary result of their inability to stand erect in their leaf-roofed highways? In digging, the snout is much used to thrust aside the earth, and they sometimes “root” with it, like hogs, in search of particles of food slightly buried in the bottom of the cage, and often eat these without taking them in their paws at all. My specimens were fed upon acorns and corn, and the entire grain of the latter was eaten. But they had all been taken in the woods, and could never have seen this food before, and were doubtless ignorant of the method adopted by their cultivated cousins, living in the prairie corn-fields, which, with a very objectionable refinement of taste, eat out only the germ, and thus destroy far more than they would by eating the whole grain. My caged specimens refused to eat flesh of any kind. This species, indeed, is probably less carnivorous than the Arvicola austerus.

I am not informed as to the extent to which this meadow-mouse is injurious here, but in timber-farms it is doubtless as great a pest—and in the same manner—as the prairie species, when equally abundant. Stumps left in fields form favorite retreats for them, from which they are not easily dislodged.

Pipfrosch Press Taxonomy Notes

Note: This section does not appear in the original article.

Arvicola scalopsoides [Audubon and Bachman, 1841] is now considered to be a junior synonym of Microtus pinetorum [Le Conte, 1830]. Several subspecies are described, Illinois falls within the range of the subspecies M. p. scalopsoides [Audubon and Bachman, 1841] although many no longer recognize the validity of any subspecies within M. pinetorum.

This species is currently referred to using the common name ‘Woodland Vole’.

For more information on the Woodland Vole, see:

Mammalian Species № 147: DOI:10.1093/mspecies/147.1
ITIS Report for TSN 180314

[1] The author did not specify the authority for Arvicola scalopsoides. The correct authority of [Audubon and Bachman, 1841] has been added.

[2] The identity of the binomial name Sorex dekayi is not clear to me. That binomial is no longer valid but I have not found a reference pointing towards the currently used binomial name that it corresponds with. The author is clearly referencing a shrew. The genus Sorex [Linnaeus, 1758] is used for shrews and both DeKay as well as Audobon and Bachman referenced a shrew with the name “DeKay’s Shrew” (Sorex dekayi) and the author also references the species as a shrew. My suspicion is that the shrew the author is referencing is probably Blarina brevicauda [Say, 1823; TSN 179967].

Glossary of Terms

abscess
A cavity caused by tissue destruction, usually because of infection, filled with pus and surrounded by inflamed tissue. Wiktionary 2020 August 03
allele
A genetic variation of a gene. Please not that in non-academic conversation, the word gene is often used where the word allele should be used. For example, we all have the same genes, what makes people have genetically individual characterists are different variations of those genes we all have, and those variations are properly referred to as alleles, not genes.
arboreal
Dwelling primarily in the trees.
arvicolae
The author uses this term interchangeably with meadow-mice, which are now often referred to as voles.
binomial name
Sometimes also referred to as ‘binomial nomenclature’. The specified taxonomy Genus and Species assigned to a biological life form. For example, the Gray Wolf has the binomial name Canis lupus. See also trinomial name.
bring forth
An idiom to indicate the bearing of young.
carnivorous
Feeds upon animals.
conchologist
One who studies mollusk shells.
congener
A member of the same taxonomy genus.
congenial
pleasant and familiar, safe.
corn crib
A building originally designed by the indigenous peoples of the Americas and later adopted by the European colonies who then spread the design back to Europe. It is designed to protect harvested corn—still on the cob—from the elements while retaining outside air flow, allowing the corn to dry. Corn cribs are usually elevated to reduce predation by pests.
corn shock
Before modern mechanized harvesting techniques were developed, in the fall when corn was harvested it often be dried by bundling corn stalks together vertically and left in the field to dry. These bundles were called corn shocks. See Photo 24. The Amish still use this technique.
cryptic species complex
A group of two or more closely related yet distinct species that are either difficult or impossible to distinguish from each other based upon morphological features alone.
depredation
Consumption of agricultural resources to the loss of the farmer.
The author frequently uses this term incorrectly to simply mean tamed; living as a pet that has learned to accept captivity. The actual meaning however is a lineage of plants or animals that have been through a process of selective breeding by humans so that they now differ, often considerably, from their wild form for a beneficial purpose to man; often with the result of changed natural history should they be required to survive without man caring for them.
domiciled
Established as resident.
enemy
In the context of natural history, a species that kills another species, often but not always for food, is sometimes referred to as an ‘enemy’.
et cetera
An indication that a list continues with additional items that are similar to the previously specified items. Typically abbreviated, as &c. historically but more commonly in the present with etc.
fecundity
Number, rate, or capacity of offspring production. Wiktionary 2020 July 08
forenoon
Archaic synonym for morning; the time between sunrise and noon.
girdle
To kill or stunt a tree by removing or inverting a ring of bark. Wiktionary 2020 July 08
gravid
Synonymous with pregnant. In recent years, it is no longer customary to use gravid in the context of mammals, but it is still frequently used in the context of reptiles, live-bearing fish, and some invertebrates.
haunts
locations of habitation.
horde
A numerically large grouping of organisms; typically used in the context of a migration from one location to another.
idiom
An established expression whose meaning is not deducible from the literal meanings of its component words, often peculiar to a given language. Wiktionary 2020 August 03
inclement
Severe; unrelenting. Usually used in the context of weather.
indigenous peoples
The ethnic people groups who inhabited a land prior to the recording of modern written history. Also often referred to as ‘First Nations’ or ‘Native Peoples’.
injurious
harmful; causing loss of crops or livestock in the context of farming.
ITIS
Abbreviation for Intergrated Taxonomic Information System. An online database with “authoritative taxonomic information on plants, animals, fungi, and microbes of North America and the world.” The database is available to the public at https://www.itis.gov/.
larva
Usually used with insects and amphibians. A life stage after birth or hatching but prior to metamorphosis into the adult form. Pluralized as larvae.
mamma
The milk secreting organ of mammals. Pluralized as mammae.
mast
In the context of botany, the fruit of forest trees and shrubs; acorns and other nuts.
masticate
To chew, often in the context of extended chewing, such as the chewing of cud.
melanin
Any of a group of naturally occurring dark pigments, especially the pigment found in skin, hair, fur, and feathers.Wiktionary 2020 August 03
melanism
The excessive production of melanin in an organism rulting in a black or very dark coloration that is often atypical for the species.
melanistic
Having the property of melanism
metamorphosis
The morphological transition some animals go through from one life stage into their next (often adult) life stage.
milldam
A dam constructed to create a mill pond, using water that overflows the dam to turn a water wheel.
milk (corn)
A stage during the development of corn where the kernels are mostly yellow and contain a milky white fluid. See the Purdue University web page Kernel Development Stages in Corn for more information.
morphological
The observable physical characteristics of an organism.
myriad
Large quantity or number.
Name Authority
Often just referred to as ‘authority’. When a taxonomy rank, binomial name, or trinomial name is specified; the name of the naturalist considered to be the authority for that rank or name is often also specified. Usually the name of the naturalist and the year of the authoritative description is given, in some cases the ITIS Taxonomic Serial Number (TSN) is also specified, when one exists. When an authority is used with a binomial name, the authority usually refers to the naturalist associated with describing the Species rank even if the Genus rank differs from their description. When used with a trinomial name, the authority usually referes to the naturalist associated with describing the Subspecies rank, even if that naturalist originally assigned it as a now-invalidated Species rank. It should be noted that in some cases, especially where taxonomy confusion exists, the authority may not reference the first naturalist to use the rank name. Pipfrosch Press always encapsulates the authority within square brackets. In zoology, sometimes the abbreviation L. is used in an authority to indicate Linnaeus (or Linné if after 1761 when he was granted nobility status). Botany has some additional common authority abbreviations.
pecuniary
Fiscally or monetary.
plumbeous
Of a dull gray lead-like color.
pomologist
A person who studies fruits and the cultivation of of fruits.
pugnacious
Naturally aggressive or hostile. Wiktionary 2020 July 09
pupa
The life stage of an insect during the metamorphosis transition, often taking place within a shell the larva creates called a cocoon. Pluralized as pupae.
quadruped
In the general sense, any animal that uses four limbs for locomotion. It differs from the term tetrapod in that tetrapods include animals that at one point in their evolutionary history had four limbs but no longer do—such as snakes—and tetrapod also includes species with four limbs but have adapted to bipedal (two limb) locomotion. However even though the quadruped technically applies to many reptiles and amphibians, quadruped is generally used to refer to mammals that use four limbs for locomotion.
rapacious
Predatory, typically in reference to predators that hunt down and seize live prey, usually in reference to vertebrate prey. In modern times, this term is usually only used in the context of rapacious birds but historically it also has been heavily used in the context of rapacious mammals.
reconnoiter
To perform a reconnaissance (of an area; an enemy position); to scout with the aim of gaining information. Wiktionary 2020 July 27
rod
When used as a unit of measure, a rod is 16½ feet which is approximately five meters.
rudimentary
Basic or minimal. Archaic form: rudimental.
scientific name
The taxonomy binomial or trinomial name assigned to a species or subspecies.
spermophile
Ground squirrels and burrowing squirrel-like rodents. See page 73b.
taxonomy
A system of grouping life forms into hierarchical categories to assist in their study. The standard categories, in hierarchical order, are Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus, and Species. In some cases, super or sub prefixes are used with those categories to indicate an additional category level before or after one of those categories, with ‘Subspecies’ being the most commonly encountered additional category by the layman.
trinomial name
Sometimes also referred to as ‘trinomial nomenclature’. The specified taxonomy Genus, Species, and Subpecies assigned to a biological life form. For example, the Mexican Gray Wolf has the trinomial name Canis lupus baileyi. See also binomial name.

A bone in the spinal column. Pluralized as vertebrae.